<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="City of Balt., Md., Ord. 26-104" codify:doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Code">
  <num type="law">26-104</num>
  <num type="bill">26-0152</num>
  <heading type="short">Installment Payment Plans – Property Taxes in Arrears – Residential Property</heading>
  <heading type="long">An Ordinance Concerning Installment Payment Plans – Property Taxes in Arrears – Residential Property</heading>
  <meta>
    <stub/>
    <introduced>2026-02-23</introduced>
    <effective>2026-04-27</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="ord" url="./enacted/26-104.pdf">Ord. 26-104</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <vote date="2026-02-23" reading="first"/>
      <vote date="2026-04-27" reading="second"/>
      <enacted>2026-04-27</enacted>
      <committee>Favorable</committee>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section>
    <prefix>Section</prefix>
    <num>1</num>
    <codify:insert path="28|II" after="7A" codified:doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Code" codified:path="28|§7B-1|annos">
      <container>
        <prefix>Subtitle</prefix>
        <num>7B</num>
        <heading>Installment Payments for Taxes in Arrears</heading>
        <section>
          <prefix>§</prefix>
          <num>7B-1</num>
          <heading>Definitions.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <heading>In general.</heading>
            <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <heading>Department.</heading>
            <text>"Department" means the Baltimore City Department of Finance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <heading>Director.</heading>
            <text>"Director" means the Baltimore City Director of Finance or the Director's designee.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <heading>Dwelling.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <heading>In general.</heading>
              <text>"Dwelling" means:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>a building that is used, in whole or in part, for residential occupancy; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>the lot or curtilage on which the building is erected.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <heading>Inclusions.</heading>
              <text>"Dwelling" includes:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>a condominium unit;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>an apartment in a cooperative apartment corporation; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <text>a part of real property used other than primarily for residential purposes, if the real property is used as a principal residence by an individual who has a legal interest in the real property.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <heading>Eligible property.</heading>
            <text>"Eligible property" means any property that has a dwelling.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <heading>Property.</heading>
            <text>"Property" means any unit of real property that is subject to the real property tax of Baltimore City.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <prefix>§</prefix>
          <num>7B-2</num>
          <heading>Installment payment program.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <heading>Establishment.</heading>
            <text>The Director shall establish an installment payment program:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>in which any person with a legal interest in an eligible property may enroll; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>that allows any person with a legal interest in an eligible property to:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>make payment of taxes in arrears on an eligible property; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>make payment of any fee or charge of any kind that is included on a property tax bill for that eligible property.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <heading>Compliance with installment payment plan.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <heading>Determination of compliance.</heading>
              <text>A person is not in compliance with the terms of an installment payment plan if the minimum payment on that installment payment plan is not made for a period of 90 days after the date the payment is due.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <heading>Prohibition against action if in compliance.</heading>
              <text>If a person is in compliance with the terms of an installment payment plan under this section, the Director may not take action under Title 14, Subtitle 8 of the State Tax-Property Article {"Collection"} to collect any property taxes in arrears that are included in the installment payment plan.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <heading>Remedies available if not in compliance.</heading>
              <text>If a person is not in compliance with the terms of an installment payment plan, the Director may:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>terminate the person's installment payment plan; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>take action under Title 14, Subtitle 8 of the State Tax-Property Article {"Collection"} to collect the property taxes in arrears that were included in the installment payment plan.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <heading>Notice.</heading>
            <text>Each offer of an installment payment plan shall:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>include the availability of an installment payment plan;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>state the minimum terms of the plan that would be acceptable to the Director;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>explain any alternate terms that may be available;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>state the date by which the Department must be contacted to enter into an installment payment plan;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>indicate the name and telephone number of a Department representative that a person may call to discuss the installment payment program; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>state what action the Department may take if the person does not enter into an installment payment plan by the date specified in paragraph (4) of this subsection.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <heading>Terms of plan.</heading>
            <text>An installment payment plan shall set forth:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>the total amount and dates of the delinquent charges covered by the plan;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>the total value of the plan, if different than the amount in paragraph (1) of this subsection;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>the time period over which the total amount shall be paid;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>the number, due date, and amount of each installment payment due under the plan; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>whether invoices will be sent by mail or electronic means.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <heading>Plan statement.</heading>
            <text>The Department shall send to a person with an installment payment plan a statement that provides 30 days' notice of each installment payment due under the plan.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <heading>Annual report.</heading>
            <text>On or before July 1 of each year, the Department shall provide to the Mayor and City Council a report that contains the following information:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>the total number of persons enrolled in an active installment payment plan and the average amount of arrearage for all plans;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>the total number of persons that entered into an installment payment plan in the prior fiscal year and the average amount of arrearage;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>the number of persons enrolled in an installment payment plan that are not in compliance with the plan and the average amount of arrearage;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>a summary of the resources that are available to assist a person that is not in compliance with an installment payment plan;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>a summary of the outreach conducted by the Department to encourage people to enroll in an installment payment agreement; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>any additional information requested by the Director that is relevant to property tax arrearages and installment payment agreements authorized under this subtitle.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <prefix>§</prefix>
          <num>7B-3</num>
          <heading>Rules and regulations.</heading>
          <text>Subject to <cite path="|general|4" doc="City of Balt., Md., Ord. 26-104">Title 4 {"Administrative Procedure Act – Regulations"}</cite> of the <cite path="|general" doc="City of Balt., Md., Ord. 26-104">City General Provisions Article</cite>, the Director may adopt rules and regulations to carry out the provisions of this subtitle.</text>
        </section>
      </container>
    </codify:insert>
    <codify:replace path="28|§8-6|(c)" codified:doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Code" codified:path="28|§8-6|(c)">
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>Duties of Ombudsman.</heading>
        <text>The Ombudsman shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>assist homeowners to understand the process for collection of delinquent taxes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>actively assist homeowners to apply for tax credits, discount programs, and other public benefits that may assist the homeowners to pay delinquent taxes and improve their financial situation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>refer homeowners to legal services, housing counseling, and other social services that may assist homeowners to pay delinquent taxes and improve their financial situation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>maintain a website that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>functions as a clearinghouse for information concerning:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>the process for collection of delinquent taxes; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>services and programs that are available to assist homeowners to pay delinquent taxes and improve their financial situation; and</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>includes:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>a notice regarding eligibility to enroll in an installment payment plan;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>a complete description of the installment payment programs established under Subtitles 7A and 7B of this article; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>detailed instructions on how to enroll in the installment payment programs established under Subtitles 7A and 7B of this article.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </codify:replace>
  </section>
</document>
