<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-214-1, Part III</num>
  <heading>Acting Agency or Bureau Heads Out-of-Title Work (Substitution)</heading>
  <para name="scope">
    <heading>SCOPE</heading>
    <text>This section governs out-of-title compensation for acting agency or bureau heads.  An employee may not voluntarily perform the duties of the out-of-title class nor be assigned these duties without receiving out-of-title compensation.  Out-of-title work is intended to be temporary in nature and is the result of a position becoming vacant.  Out-of-title compensation can also be received by an employee subject to the eligibility requirements of this policy if the incumbent agency or bureau head is incapacitated, or otherwise not available, for a period which exceeds 30 consecutive calendar days.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="eligibility">
    <heading>ELIGIBILITY</heading>
    <text>An employee who has been officially assigned by a written MEMO from the appropriate appointing authority to perform the job duties an agency or bureau head will receive out-of-title compensation provided that all of the following conditions are met:</text>
    <text><strong>∙</strong>	The position of agency or bureau head has become vacant and the employee has performed the duties of the higher class for 30 consecutive days.</text>
    <text><strong>∙</strong>	A certified list of eligibles is not available from the Civil Service Commission.  If a list is not available, steps must be initiated by the appropriate appointing authority to fill the position permanently subject to the rules of the Civil Service Commission.</text>
    <text><strong>∙</strong>	The appointing officer responsible for the vacant position has submitted to the Civil Service Commission a REQUEST FOR CERTIFICATION OF ELIGIBLES, if available, or a REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION, if applicable.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="amount-of-compensation">
    <heading>AMOUNT OF COMPENSATION</heading>
    <text>An employee fitting the definition of out-of-title work and pursuant to the eligibility requirements will be compensated by an amount equal to 50% of the difference between the present salary being earned by the employee in his permanent position and classification and the amount the employee would be paid if promoted to the higher class.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="effective-dates">
    <heading>EFFECTIVE DATES</heading>
    <text>An employee authorized for out-of-title pay will receive the higher rate of pay effective the first full payroll period following the 30 consecutive calendar days period of performing the duties of the higher class or following the request for an eligible list, whichever occurs last.</text>
    <text>Compensation for out-of-title pay ceases when a new appointee assumes the duties of the position or the appointing officer terminates the out-of-title assignment.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="implementation">
    <heading>IMPLEMENTATION</heading>
    <text>To implement the out-of-title salary change, a <strong>CHANGE NOTICE</strong> (28-1618-5143)  {<cite path="§AM-205-4-5">AM-205-4-5</cite>}must be submitted to the Civil Service Commission for subsequent forwarding to the Central Payroll Division.  No written entries are required on the PAYROLL ATTENDANCE REPORT.</text>
    <text>At the conclusion of the out-of-title assignment, a <strong>CHANGE NOTICE</strong> must be processed through the Civil Service Commission to the Central Payroll Division.  This notice adjusts the employee's out-of-title pay to the rate of his permanent position and classification.</text>
  </para>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" effective="1988-11-01" display="true">November 1, 1988</annotation>
  </annotations>
</section>
