<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-204-1, Part III</num>
  <heading>Holiday Compensation</heading>
  <para name="scope">
    <heading>SCOPE</heading>
    <text>This policy is concerned with holiday compensation for City employees who have been in pay status for at least one (1) day in the payroll period in which the holiday occurs. Permanent full-time employees not scheduled to work on these dates will receive their regular rate of pay. A permanent part-time employee will receive his/her regular rate of pay as holiday compensation providing the observance the holiday falls on the employee's regularly scheduled workday.</text>
    <text>City employees who are eligible to receive holiday compensation and who are scheduled to work on a City holiday will be compensated according to their classification under the Fair Labor Standards Act (FLSA) as non-exempt or exempt employees. Employees who are eligible to receive holiday compensation and who are not required to work on a City holiday will be granted their regular rate of pay for the day on which the holiday is observed.</text>
    <text>FLSA ELIGIBILITY</text>
    <text>NON-EXEMPT EMPLOYEES (CODE F):</text>
    <text>Code F employees required to work on a holiday will be compensated either at a pay rate of time and one-half for each hour worked, or compensatory leave computed at a rate of time and one-half for each hour worked.</text>
    <text>EXEMPT EMPLOYEES (CODE X):</text>
    <text>Code X employees required to work on a holiday will be compensated by receiving their regular pay, plus compensatory leave in an amount equivalent to the hours worked.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="double-shift-work">
    <heading>DOUBLE SHIFT WORK</heading>
    <text>Code F employees who normally are engaged in shift work and are required to work a regular shift, plus a second shift on the holiday, will receive normal pay for each of the two shifts worked, plus pay or compensatory leave at the rate of time and one-half for all hours worked on both shifts.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="chargeable-leave">
    <heading>CHARGEABLE LEAVE</heading>
    <text>Employees scheduled to work on holiday and who cannot report for duty because of sickness will be charged sick leave for that day provided it is reported in the first hour of the shift to the supervisor and the employee has accrued sick leave to cover the occurrence. Failure to properly notify the supervisor of the sick occurrence as stipulated in this policy will result in a payroll marking of "X" and a complete loss of pay for the day.</text>
    <text>An employee authorized a sick leave marking immediately prior to a holiday who is not scheduled to work the holiday will not be charged sick leave for the holiday.</text>
    <text>An official City holiday which occurs on an employee's vacation leave day or personal leave day will not be deducted from the employee's vacation or personal leave balances.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="temporary-or-seasonal-employees">
    <heading>TEMPORARY OR SEASONAL EMPLOYEES</heading>
    <text>Temporary or seasonal employees, including provisional employees, are not eligible to receive holiday compensation. If such employees are required to work on a holiday, they will be compensated for such work at their regular rate of pay.</text>
  </para>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" effective="1987-09-25" display="true">September 25, 1987</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" effective="1999-09-02" display="true">September 2, 1999</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-204-1, Part I">AM-204-1 PART I</cite> ANNUAL HOLIDAYS</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-204-1, Part II">AM-204-1 PART II</cite> ELECTION DAYS</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-204-2">AM-204-2</cite> VACATION LEAVE</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-204-4">AM-204-4</cite> PERSONAL LEAVE</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-204-14">AM-204-14</cite> SICK LEAVE</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-291-1">AM-291-1</cite> CIVIL SERVICE CLASSES</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-291-2">AM-291-2</cite> NON-CIVIL SERVICE CLASSES</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-234-1">AM-234-1</cite> TEMPORARY OR SEASONAL APPOINTMENTS</annotation>
  </annotations>
</section>
