<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-227-1-1</num>
  <heading>Procedures for Avoiding Opportunity for Physical Attack</heading>
  <text>All employees should be aware of their daily work surroundings, both the physical layout and the employees with whom they work. This is especially important for those employees who work outside a "traditional" office environment. These may include a remote job site, fueling depot, warehouse, testing lab, etc. Particular attention should be paid at locations where fellow employees come and go frequently, driving to multiple locations largely unsupervised.</text>
  <text>Once identified, a potentially violent or disturbed person should not be left alone with other employees. Potentially violent or disturbed persons should be closely observed and monitored. These employees should be escorted to a private area away from onlookers. Trained supervisors should determine the appropriate course of action. (See page 3 of <cite path="§AM-227-1">AM-227-1</cite>, Supervisor Responsibilities.)</text>
  <text>If an employee has become involved in a non-criminal dispute with family members or others, or if the employee has disclosed that he or she is a victim of domestic violence and the employee has obtained an "Order of Protection", an "Injunction Against Harassment" or a similar court order, the employee should be instructed to include the employee's work location, as well as the place of residence, in the order. The employee should notify his or her supervisor of such an order and provide a description or recent photograph(s) of the individual(s) cited in the order.</text>
  <text>As a general rule, work sites should be reasonably secured. Alarms, television monitors, intercoms, panic buttons, electric latch devices or electronic card key devices may be helpful means of securing a work area, but most office locations may need little more than secure standard key locks or a card key system. Management should consider any additional security devices after a careful risk assessment.</text>
  <text>
    <strong>Removing Motivations for Violence</strong>
  </text>
  <text>Along with avoiding the opportunity for physical attack, employees should avoid antagonizing others and creating hard feelings. Defusing a potentially violent person requires self-control, tact, judgment and patience. Some suggestions are:</text>
  <text>
    <ul>
      <li>Remain calm and try to keep everyone else calm.</li>
      <li>Avoid a win-lose situation, especially in front of spectators.</li>
      <li>Let the person sit down, relax and calm down in private.</li>
      <li>Listen to what the employee or citizen has to say without arguing or challenging.</li>
      <li>Do not be critical, judgmental or sarcastic.</li>
      <li>If any threat of violence is made, warn the person that threats of violence are taken very seriously and are not acceptable.</li>
      <li>Surrender property during a robbery.</li>
      <li>Appear agreeable (even temporarily) to the person's demands if possible.</li>
    </ul>
  </text>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" effective="2010-09-29" display="true">September 29, 2010</annotation>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM-227-1" type="Related Policies"/>
  </annotations>
</section>
