<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-213-1</num>
  <para>
    <prefix>Part</prefix>
    <num>I</num>
    <heading>Reinstatement</heading>
    <para name="scope">
      <heading>SCOPE</heading>
      <text>An individual may be reinstated to a position in the same job classification from which he/she voluntarily resigned provided that not more than one (1) year has transpired since the employee's resignation. The position does not have to be in the same agency from which the employee resigned.</text>
      <text>For reinstatement, the employee's entry date will be adjusted to reflect the period of absence. Vacation leave accrual rates and longevity-based salary increments will be based on the adjusted entry date. Any unpaid sick leave will be adjusted and restored.</text>
      <text>If more than one (1) year has lapsed since the employee's resignation, the individual must follow the normal rules for applying for City government employment. Benefits are not restored. This policy, however, does not apply to the calculation of Employees' Retirement System service that is defined in <cite doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Code" path="|22">Article 22 of the Baltimore City Code</cite>.</text>
      <text>This Policy does not apply to City or Baltimore Police Department employees seeking reinstatement with the Baltimore Police Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para name="reinstatement-process">
      <heading>REINSTATEMENT PROCESS</heading>
      <text>To be reinstated to a Civil Service position, an individual must contact the Department of Human Resources by letter relative to the request. If after investigation by the Department of Human Resources, it is determined that a position in the same classification from which the individual resigned is vacant, that funds are available for the position, and that the agency head wants to accept the employee, then the Department of Human Resources may approve the reinstatement request and notify the individual and the agency.</text>
      <text>The hiring process may be initiated in accordance with established policies after Department of Human Resources approval of the reinstatement. To be reinstated to a non-Civil Service position, the individual must contact the appointing officer.</text>
      <text>To resolve questions concerning adjusted entry date, leave accrual and sick leave balance, the hiring agency's human resources/personnel officer is asked to oversee the completion of AM-213- 1-1, a form to document this information for the employee and agency. Employees are requested to complete the top portion of the form at the time of reentry and return it to the human resources/personnel office of the hiring agency. The human resources/personnel office inserts the reentry date and forwards the form to the Central Payroll Division for completion. The form is returned to the hiring agency where it is reviewed and signed by the human resources/personnel officer. The human resources/personnel officer forwards a copy of the completed form to the Retirement Systems, gives a copy to the employee and the original becomes part of the employee's</text>
      <text>personnel record. Discrepancies should be resolved in a reasonable time frame; however, the employee has 18 months in which to place a claim to the hiring agency for prior creditable service.</text>
    </para>
    <para name="salary-determination">
      <heading>SALARY DETERMINATION</heading>
      <text>An employee who is reinstated to a position within a year from the date of separation shall be reentered either at the classification's entry level salary or at one salary level lower than the employee's salary level which he/she had been receiving at the time of separation, whichever is higher. After placement on the salary scale, appropriate longevity moneys will be restored. Employees must observe a full eighteen (18) month period before moving to the next level.</text>
    </para>
    <para name="probation-period">
      <heading>PROBATION PERIOD</heading>
      <text>There is no probation period requirement for an employee who is reinstated to a previously held classification provided that the requirement was satisfied during the original appointment. Vacation may be used as it is earned.</text>
    </para>
    <para name="benefits-determination">
      <heading>BENEFITS DETERMINATION</heading>
      <text>
        <u>Entry Date</u>
      </text>
      <text>The original entry date of an employee who is reinstated shall be restored and then adjusted for the period transpired between separation and reinstatement subject to the one year reinstatement period. This entry date will be the official entry date and will be the basis for determining vacation leave accrual rates and longevity based salary increments.</text>
      <text>
        <u>Sick Leave</u>
      </text>
      <text>An individual who is reinstated will be credited with 50% of sick leave balance that was not converted to cash at the time of termination. (See <cite path="§AM-205-7">AM-205-7</cite>).</text>
      <text>Upon reinstatement a former employee who voluntarily separated may not repurchase sick leave for which he/she was paid.</text>
      <text>
        <u>Health Care</u>
      </text>
      <text>The Employees Benefits Section of the Department of Human Resources must be contacted for information on the health care benefits available to a reinstated employee.</text>
      <text>
        <u>Retirement Systems</u>
      </text>
      <text>The Employees' Retirement Systems must be contacted for information on Retirement System service credit for the reinstated employee.</text>
    </para>
    <para name="drug/alcohol-testing-and-physical-exam-requirement">
      <heading>DRUG/ALCOHOL TESTING AND PHYSICAL EXAM REQUIREMENT</heading>
      <text>Prior to reinstatement, all individuals are required to take pre-placement drug and alcohol screenings at the City of Baltimore Occupational Medical Services (Mercy Clinic) at 323 N. Calvert Street. The agency human resources/personnel office or designee must schedule an appointment for the testing by FAX: 410-332-0614. When reporting for the scheduled appointment, the individual must bring photo identification, along with the completed Management/HR Administration Drug/Alcohol Testing Order, (form # 28-1608-5156).</text>
      <text>Only those individuals being considered for reinstatement in the following categories will be required to undergo physicals:</text>
      <text>
        <ul proof="needed">
          <li>All Commercial Drivers License (CDL) holders</li>
          <li>All employees who are required to frequently lift over 40 lbs.</li>
          <li>All health care workers</li>
          <li>All employees with potential exposure to hazardous materials, (ex. Chemicals, rodenticides, herbicides, lead, asbestos)</li>
          <li>All employees with exposure to noise in excess of 85 decibels</li>
          <li>All employees who are candidates for vaccination, (ex. hepatitis B, rabies)</li>
          <li>All employees who wear respirators</li>
        </ul>
      </text>
      <text>The agency human resources/personnel office or designee must schedule an appointment for the physical by FAX: 410-332-0614. For the scheduled appointment, the individual must bring photo identification, along with the completed Request for Services form (form #28-1608-5153) and the Management/HR Administration Drug/Alcohol Testing Order, (form # 28-1608-5156).</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </para>
  <para>
    <prefix>Part</prefix>
    <num>II</num>
    <heading>Subsequent Employment after Voluntary Separation from City Service</heading>
    <para name="scope">
      <heading>SCOPE</heading>
      <text>Subsequent employment pertains to employees who resign after the effective date of this policy and return to City government employment in a different classification than they previously held, within one (1) year of their voluntary termination. This category is different from reinstatement because the individual is not returning to the same job classification. An employee returning to the same classification is covered under <cite path="§AM-213-1, Part I">AM-213-1, Part I</cite>, Reinstatement.</text>
      <text>For the subsequent employment category, the employee's entry date will be adjusted to reflect the period of absence. Any unpaid sick leave will be adjusted and restored. Vacation leave accrual rates will be based on the adjusted entry date and the Memorandum of Understanding for the employee's representation in the new job classification.</text>
      <text>If more than one (1) year has transpired, the individual will be considered a new hire without an adjusted entry date. Benefits are not restored. This policy, however, does not apply to the calculation of Employees' Retirement System service that is defined in <cite doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Code" path="|22">Article 22 of the Baltimore City Code</cite>.</text>
      <text>This Policy does not apply to City or Baltimore Police Department employees seeking reinstatement with the Baltimore Police Department</text>
    </para>
    <para name="subsequent-employment-process">
      <heading>SUBSEQUENT EMPLOYMENT PROCESS</heading>
      <text>An individual may be considered for the benefits of subsequent employment with City government provided that the person is hired to a different classification than previously held and not more than one year has transpired since the employee's voluntary resignation from the City. For the purposes of hiring, the employee must follow the normal rules for applying for City government employment.</text>
      <text>To resolve questions concerning adjusted entry date, leave accrual and sick leave balance, the hiring agency's human resources/personnel officer is asked to oversee the completion of <cite path="§AM-213-1-1">AM-213-1-1</cite>, a form to document this information for the employee and agency. Employees are requested to complete the top portion of the form at the time of reentry and return it to the human resources/personnel office of the hiring agency. The human resources/personnel office inserts the reentry date and forwards the form to the Central Payroll Division for completion. The form is returned to the hiring agency where it is reviewed and signed by the human resources/personnel officer. The human resources/personnel officer forwards a copy of the completed form to the Retirement Systems, gives a copy to the employee and the original becomes part of the employee's personnel record. Discrepancies should be resolved in a reasonable time frame; however, the employee has 18 months in which to place a claim to the hiring agency for prior creditable service.</text>
    </para>
    <para name="salary-determination">
      <heading>SALARY DETERMINATION</heading>
      <text>An employee who is hired to a position within one (1) year from the date of separation will be hired at the entry level grade of the class unless approved for higher salary by the Director of Human Resources in accordance with <cite path="§AM-205-1">AM-205-1</cite>. For eligible employees, longevity increments based on years of service will be restored according to the adjusted entry date and the representative organization of the current job classification. Employees must observe a full eighteen (18) month period before moving to the next level.</text>
    </para>
    <para name="probationary-period">
      <heading>PROBATIONARY PERIOD</heading>
      <text>The employee will be required to serve a probationary period if selected to fill a vacant position in the Classified Civil Service. The probationary period of six (6) months is required to assess the employee's competency to fulfill the duties of the position. The employee may not use earned vacation leave until the probationary period is satisfactorily completed. With the concurrence of the supervisor, sick leave or personal leave may be used during the probationary period.</text>
    </para>
    <para name="benefits">
      <heading>BENEFITS</heading>
      <text>
        <u>Entry Date</u>
      </text>
      <text>The original entry date of an employee who is subsequently employed shall be restored and then adjusted for the period transpired between separation and reentry, as long as the period is no longer than one (1) year. The adjusted entry date will be the basis for determining vacation leave accrual rates and longevity- based salary increments, as outlined in the new job classification.</text>
      <text>
        <u>Sick Leave</u>
      </text>
      <text>An individual who is subsequently employed will be credited with 50% of sick leave balance, which was not converted to cash at the time of termination. (See <cite path="§AM-205-7">AM-205-7</cite>).</text>
      <text>Upon re-entry, a former employee who voluntarily separated may not repurchase sick leave for which he/she was paid.</text>
      <text>
        <u>Health Care</u>
      </text>
      <text>The Employees' Benefits Section of the Department of Human Resources must be contacted for information on the health care benefits available for subsequent employment.</text>
      <text>
        <u>Retirement Systems</u>
      </text>
      <text>The Employees' Retirement Systems must be contacted for information on Retirement System service credit for the employee in the subsequent employment category.</text>
    </para>
    <para name="drug/alcohol-testing-and-physical-exam-requirement">
      <heading>DRUG/ALCOHOL TESTING AND PHYSICAL EXAM REQUIREMENT</heading>
      <text>In the subsequent employment category, all individuals are required to take pre-placement drug and alcohol screenings at the City of Baltimore Occupational Medical Services (Mercy Clinic) at 323 N. Calvert Street. The agency human resources/personnel office or designee must schedule an appointment for the testing by FAX: 410-332-0614. When reporting for the scheduled appointment, the individual must bring photo identification, along with the completed Management/HR Administration Drug/Alcohol</text>
      <text>Testing Order, (form # 28-1608-5156).</text>
      <text>Only those individuals being considered for subsequent employment in the following categories will be required to undergo physicals:</text>
      <text>
        <ul proof="needed">
          <li>All Commercial Drivers License (CDL) holders</li>
          <li>All employees who are required to frequently lift over 40 lbs.</li>
          <li>All health care workers</li>
          <li>All employees with potential exposure to hazardous materials, (ex. Chemicals, rodenticides, herbicides, lead, asbestos)</li>
          <li>All employees with exposure to noise in excess of 85 decibels</li>
          <li>All employees who are candidates for vaccination, (ex. hepatitis B, rabies)</li>
          <li>All employees who wear respirators</li>
        </ul>
      </text>
      <text>The agency human resources/personnel office or designee must schedule an appointment for the physical by FAX: 410-332-0614. For the scheduled appointment, the individual must bring photo identification, along with the completed Request for Services form (form #28-1608-5153) and the Management/HR Administration Drug/Alcohol Testing Order, (form # 28-1608-5156).</text>
    </para>
  </para>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" effective="2003-04-24" display="true">April 24, 2003</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" effective="2017-09-27" display="true">September 27, 2017</annotation>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM-204-30|I" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM-204-31|II" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM-204-12" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM-205-7" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM-205-9" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM-205-13" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM 213-1|II" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM 213-1-1" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM-231-1" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation type="History" effective="2003-04-04" display="true">April 4, 2003</annotation>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM-205-1" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM-213-1|I" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM-213-1-1" type="Related Policies"/>
  </annotations>
</section>
