<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-241-1-1</num>
  <heading>Employee Layoff Checklist</heading>
  <text>
    <table>
      <thead>
        <tr>
          <th>Effective Date and Initial</th>
          <th>Layoff Action</th>
        </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <p>_________________</p>
            <p>Date</p>
            <p>_________________</p>
            <p>Agency HR Practitioner Initial</p>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p>
              <strong>Sixty (60) Days Before Layoff</strong>
            </p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">1. Agency Heads shall determine job classifications and organizational units from which employee(s) will be laid off. The layoff lists are developed using the criteria specified in this Policy or current contractual agreement or MOU, as applicable.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">2. For each organizational unit, develop a list of employees in each classification from which layoffs will occur. List employees in order of their promotion dates beginning with the least senior employee. Agency files shall retain the seniority list.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <p>_________________</p>
            <p>Date</p>
            <p>_________________</p>
            <p>Agency HR Practitioner Initial</p>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p>
              <strong>Thirty (30) Days Before Layoff</strong>
            </p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">1. Send to the OLC, DHR, Agency Equal Opportunity Officer ("Agency EEO"), and Law Department a Memorandum containing the following information on the employee(s) to be laid off:</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">a. Organizational Unit;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">b. Class number and title;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">c. Employee Name;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">d. Employee Identification Number;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">e. Position number;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">f. Entry Date;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">g. Length of service in present classification;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">h. Length of service in organizational unit;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">i. Reason for layoff;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">j. Date of layoff;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">k. Union or employee organization;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">l. Date of Birth;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">m. Gender; and</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">n. Race.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-3">Retain a copy of the Memorandum in the affected employee's official personnel file and the Agency's file.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">2. Upon receipt of the Agency's Memorandum, the OLC shall verify the layoff list and notify the appropriate union or bargaining unit of the proposed layoff; the OLC shall also verify that selection rules are followed for Civil Service positions. When a selection is invalid, the Agency must provide the OLC with new name(s) within two (2) working days. The OLC shall also notify Employee Retirement System and DHR of the affected employee's status.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">3. Upon receipt of the Agency's Memorandum, the Agency's EEO must review the proposed layoff and determine its impact on the Agency's Affirmative Action Plan.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">4. Once the list of affected employee(s) is approved, the Agency's HR Practitioner shall create a layoff package for distribution to affected employees. The following material should be included in the layoff package:</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">a. The signed layoff letter;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">b. Layoff brochure;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">c. Your Rights Under COBRA and Notice of privacy practices;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">d. Maryland Unemployment Insurance Brochure;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">e. Retirement System brochure; and</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">f. Signed memo regarding employee's indebtedness, if applicable.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <p>_________________</p>
            <p>Date</p>
            <p>_________________</p>
            <p>Agency HR Practitioner Initial</p>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p>
              <strong>Three (3) Weeks Before Layoff</strong>
            </p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">1. The Agency's EEO shall provide written comments, if any, to the Agency Head regarding the impact of the proposed layoff on the Agency's affirmative action plan.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">2. The OLC will verify that the selection of employees for layoff conforms to provisions of the contractual agreements, layoff organizational units and other selection criteria. The Labor Commissioner shall notify the appropriate unions or employee organizations of the proposed layoffs.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">3. DHR's Employee Benefits Division shall, if requested, confer with the affected employee(s) on eligible health benefit plan options. An employee's existing active health benefits coverage ends at the end of the month in which the layoff date occurs, unless informed otherwise by DHR.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">4. DHR's Recruitment Division shall, if requested, confer with the affected employee(s) on eligibility for other City positions.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <p>_________________</p>
            <p>Date</p>
            <p>_________________</p>
            <p>Agency HR Practitioner Initial</p>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p>
              <strong>Two (2) Weeks Before Layoff</strong>
            </p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">1. The Agency HR Practitioner shall meet with the affected employee, and the employee's union representative, if applicable, to discuss the layoff and pertinent information related to the layoff;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">2. The Agency HR Practitioner shall mail via certified mail, return receipt requested, the layoff letter to the affected employee's last known home address. The layoff letter shall include the following information:</p>
            <p class="text-indent-3">a. Date of layoff;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-3">b. Reason for layoff; and</p>
            <p class="text-indent-3">c. A statement that the separation from service is a result of a layoff and is through no fault of the employee.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-3">Attached to this letter must be a copy of Information for Laid-Off Employees. A copy of the signed employee layoff letter shall be sent to DHR's Policy and Compliance Division.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <p>_________________</p>
            <p>Date</p>
            <p>_________________</p>
            <p>Agency HR Practitioner Initial</p>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p>
              <strong>Day of Layoff</strong>
            </p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">1. The Agency HR Practitioner shall conduct an Exit Interview with the employee;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">2. The Agency HR Practitioner shall inform the employee of any due compensation for unused vacation leave, personal leave, sick leave, compensatory leave, as applicable, and that payment will be received in a lump sum.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">3. The Agency HR Practitioner shall, if applicable, discuss the employee's indebtedness to the City. Follow the procedure outlined in <em><cite path="§AM-205-4">AM-205-4</cite> Employee Indebtedness</em>.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">4. Complete an Employee Termination Checklist;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">5. Advise the employee to confer with the Municipal Employees Credit Union Inc. (MECU) regarding any outstanding loans and membership entitlement, if applicable. Notify MECU accordingly of employee status.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">6. Inform employee that COBRA notification will be mailed directly to the employee's last known address and that the employee has 60 (sixty) days from the date of separation to apply for COBRA benefits.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">7. Enter termination information in HRIS. The reason code should indicate layoff.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-3">d. <strong>For employees eligible to retire:</strong> The reason code should indicate <strong><u>both</u></strong> retired and lay-off.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">8. Send Central Payroll a completed and signed termination checklist and a copy of <em><cite path="§AM-205-4-1">AM-205-4-1</cite> Notification of Employee Indebtedness (Memo to Employee)</em>, if applicable.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">9. <strong>For Civil Service Employees only:</strong> No later than the affected employee(s) last day, DHR's Recruitment Division shall place the affected employee(s) on the reemployment list(s) in accordance with Civil Service Rules 39 and 52.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">10. <strong>For Retiring Employees only: </strong>No later than the affected employee(s) last day, the employee shall confer with either Employees' Retirement System or Fire or Police Employees' Retirement System so that appropriate paperwork regarding benefits is processed.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <p>_________________</p>
            <p>Date</p>
            <p>_________________</p>
            <p>Agency HR Practitioner Initial</p>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p>
              <strong>After Layoff</strong>
            </p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">1. Central Payroll shall record the following information about the laid off employee:</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">a. Conversion of sick leave days to cash;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">b. Number of sick leave days not converted to cash;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">c. Unused compensatory leave if applicable (employees should refer to their respective MOU) before payment for accumulated compensatory leave as applicable;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">d. Total length of City service;</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">e. Length of service in level of current salary grade; and</p>
            <p class="text-indent-4">f. Subject to FLSA requirements, any accrued leave may be subject to withholding due to indebtedness with the City.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-3">Once recorded, Central Payroll shall, with the consultation of the Law Department, Collections Division, prepare and issue the employee's final paycheck and payment for unused leave, minus any amount of the employee's indebtedness to the City, within thirty (30) calendar days. If an employee is indebted to the City, the employee should be advised to contact the Law Department, Collection Division.</p>
            <p class="text-indent-2">2. The Agency's HR Practitioner shall retain a copy of Central Payroll's record in the employee's official personnel file and the Agency's file.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </text>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" display="true" effective="2018-07-25">July 25, 2018 [replaces <cite path="§AM-205-8-1">AM-205-8-1</cite>]</annotation>
  </annotations>
</section>
