<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-239-1-1</num>
  <heading>Out-of-Town Travel by Elected Officials Procedure for Requesting Advance Funds or Reimbursement</heading>
  <para name="overview">
    <heading>OVERVIEW</heading>
    <text>The City of Baltimore Travel Request form (28-1418-5016) must be completed by elected officials for out-of-town business travel. If requesting advance travel funds, the form must be completed at least 20 calendar days prior to departure. If notice to travel is less than 20 calendar days, the Travel Request form does not require completion until the return from the trip; however advance funds cannot be requested. All travel requests that exceed $800 of expense must be filed with the Clerk of the Board of Estimates.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="subsistence-rate">
    <heading>SUBSISTENCE RATE</heading>
    <text>The subsistence allowance for an area not designated as a High Rate Geographic Area (HRGA) is $91per day, exclusive of the hotel tax which is to be added to the stipulated amount. For listings of HRGAs, refer to <cite path="§AM-240-5-1">AM-240-5-1</cite>. The subsistence allowance must be used to pay for the cost of the following items: lodging, food, gratuities or tips, local transportation at the conference site, miscellaneous expenses such as clothes cleaning. Original receipts are required for all lodging costs incurred in travel status for which reimbursement will be or was requested. Receipts are also required for conference registration and transportation, if applicable. A copy of a credit card statement supporting reimbursement may be accepted, if the elected official signs the credit card statement and indicates that the statement submitted serves as the original.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="advance-travel-funds">
    <heading>ADVANCE TRAVEL FUNDS</heading>
    <text>An elected official may request funds for travel prior to the date of travel by submitting a Direct Payment Order (DPO) with a completed Travel Request form to the Department of Finance, Bureau of the Budget and Management Research (BBMR), for funding approval at least 20 calendar days before departure. BBMR will forward the travel package to the Bureau of Accounting and Payroll Services, Accounts Payable Unit, for a cash advance. A minimum of 10 work days should be allowed for processing the DPO and issuing a check to the elected official.</text>
    <text>All travel requests in excess of $800 must be filed with the Clerk of the Board of Estimates at least 20 calendar days before the trip departure.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="travel-under-$800">
    <heading>TRAVEL UNDER $800</heading>
    <text>
      <u>No Cash Advance</u>
    </text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Complete a Travel Request form as soon as possible. Prepare a DPO and attach the Travel Request form.</li>
        <li>Within 10 calendar days of the return from the trip, submit to BBMR for approval of funds the following: a DPO with the completed Travel Request form attached and all of the required travel receipts.</li>
        <li>BBMR will forward the travel package to the Accounts Payable Unit to obtain the reimbursement.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
    <text>
      <u>Cash Advance Required</u>
    </text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Pre-registration for conferences and travel arrangements should be planned at least 30 calendar days or more in advance of the travel date in order to maximize City savings for air travel and registrations.</li>
        <li>Prepare a DPO and complete a Travel Request form.</li>
        <li>At least 20 calendar days before trip departure, submit to BBMR for approval of funds the following: the DPO with the completed Travel Request form attached.</li>
        <li>BBMR will forward the travel package to Accounts Payable Unit to provide a cash advance.</li>
        <li>Within 10 calendar days of returning from the trip, submit a report accounting for all required travel expenses and provide the required travel receipts to the Accounts Payable Unit.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>TRAVEL OVER $800 – Filing with the Clerk of the Board of Estimates Is Required.</strong>
    </text>
    <text>Elected officials are required to file a completed travel request form with the Clerk of the Board of Estimates at least 20 calendar days before trip departure. If less time is involved, see the section on Exception. The filing must include a transmittal memo from the elected official, which contains the travel dates, destination, purpose of the trip, and a statement certifying compliance with the subsistence rate in accordance with <cite path="§AM-240-5">AM-240-5</cite>, Subsistence Allowance, or <cite path="§AM-240-5-1">AM-240-5-1</cite>, Subsistence: High Rate Geographic Area.</text>
    <text>The Clerk of the Board of Estimates will provide a date-stamped copy of the transmittal memo to the elected official.</text>
    <text>
      <u>No Cash Advance</u>
    </text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Pre-registration for conferences and travel arrangements should be planned at least 30 calendar days or more in advance of the travel date in order to maximize City savings for air travel and registrations.</li>
        <li>Complete a Travel Request form.</li>
        <li>At least 20 calendar days before trip departure, file a transmittal memo to the Clerk of the Board of Estimates indicating travel dates, destination, purpose of the trip, and a statement certifying compliance with the subsistence rate in accordance with <cite path="§AM-240-5">AM-240-5</cite>, Subsistence Allowance, or <cite path="§AM-240-5-1">AM-240-5-1</cite>, Subsistence: High Rate Geographic Area, along with a completed Travel Request form.</li>
        <li>Prepare a DPO.</li>
        <li>Within 10 calendar days of return from the trip, submit the following to BBMR for approval of funds: the DPO with the completed Travel Request form attached, all of the required travel receipts, and a copy of the transmittal memo showing the Clerk's date-stamp.</li>
        <li>BBMR will forward the travel package to the Accounts Payable Unit to obtain the reimbursement.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
    <text>
      <u>Cash Advance Required</u>
    </text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Pre-registration for conferences and travel arrangements should be planned at least 30 calendar days or more in advance of the travel date in order to maximize City savings for air travel and registrations.</li>
        <li>Complete a Travel Request form.</li>
        <li>At least 20 calendar days before trip departure, file a transmittal memo to the Clerk of the Board of Estimates indicating the travel dates, destination, purpose of the trip, and a statement certifying compliance with the subsistence rate in accordance with <cite path="§AM-240-5">AM-240-5</cite>, Subsistence Allowance, or <cite path="§AM-240-5-1">AM-240-5-1</cite>, Subsistence: High Rate Geographic Area, along with a completed travel request form.</li>
        <li>Prepare a DPO.</li>
        <li>At least 20 calendar days before trip departure, submit to BBMR for approval of funds the following: the DPO with the completed Travel Request form attached and a copy of the transmittal memo showing the Clerk's date-stamp.</li>
        <li>BBMR will forward the travel package to Accounts Payable Unit to provide a cash advance.</li>
        <li>Within 10 calendar days of returning from the trip, submit a report accounting for all required travel expenses and provide all of the required receipts to the Accounts Payable Unit.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>
        <u>Exception</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text>In the event that the requirement for travel does not allow for the filing of the transmittal memo and Travel Request form with the Clerk of the Board of Estimates at least 20 calendar days in advance, there can be no cash advance. The filing is still required. Within 10 calendar days of returning from the trip, a report accounting for all required travel expenses with the required receipts must be submitted to the Accounts Payable Unit.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="for-all-advance-travel-funds">
    <heading>FOR ALL ADVANCE TRAVEL FUNDS</heading>
    <text><strong>Accountability </strong>– Upon return from the trip, the elected official must account for all required expenditures pertaining to advance travel funds by submitting a memo containing the following information to the Accounts Payable Unit: the elected official's name, social security number, check number corresponding to the advance funds issued, and original receipts for lodging, conference registration and transportation, if applicable. A copy of a credit card statement supporting reimbursement may be accepted, if the elected official signs the credit card statement and indicates that the statement submitted serves as the original.</text>
    <text><strong>Unexpended Funds</strong> - Unexpended travel funds must be accounted for and returned. Refunds are to be made only by check or money order to the Director of Finance, City of Baltimore. Cash should not be used. All returns of unexpended travel funds submitted to the Accounts Payable Unit will be deposited to the appropriate account from which advance travel funds were drawn<strong>.</strong></text>
    <text><strong>Insufficient Funds</strong> - If the advance travel funding was insufficient to cover business expenses incurred during the trip, elected officials may seek reimbursement.</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Less than $40 – Enter the amount on the monthly expense report with a brief explanation.</li>
        <li>More than $40 – Submit an amended Travel Request form to the Board of Estimates for approval.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
  </para>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" effective="2004-05-12" display="true">May 12, 2004</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" effective="2005-05-11" display="true">May 11, 2005</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-239-1">AM-239-1</cite> ELECTED OFFICIALS' BUSINESS EXPENSES</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-240-5">AM-240-5</cite> SUBSISTENCE ALLOWANCE</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-240-5-1">AM-240-5-1</cite> SUBSISTENCE: HIGH RATE GEOGRAPHIC AREA</annotation>
  </annotations>
</section>
