<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-205-20</num>
  <heading>Managerial and Professional Society Salary Policy</heading>
  <para name="purpose">
    <num>I.</num>
    <heading>PURPOSE</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this policy is to establish, maintain and administer a comprehensive compensation plan for all employees of the Mayor and City Council of Baltimore ("City") in the Civil and Non-Civil classifications of the Managerial and Professional Society of Baltimore, Inc. ("MAPS").  All salaries for MAPS classifications shall be administered in compliance with this policy.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="definitions">
    <num>II.</num>
    <heading>DEFINITIONS</heading>
    <text>For purposes of this policy the following definitions will apply:</text>
    <text><strong>Agency</strong> – Any Department, Office, Board, Commission or other entity of the Mayor and City Council of Baltimore having the authority to appoint employees whose salaries are administered by the Baltimore City Department of Human Resources ("DHR").</text>
    <text><strong>Base Pay </strong>– An employee's salary, which may be reported as an hourly wage, weekly, semi-monthly, monthly or annual salary, excluding shift differentials, temporary pay, benefits, overtime, or other similar non-base pay compensation.</text>
    <text><strong>Certification</strong> - A specialized course of study resulting in the receipt of a certification from a nationally recognized and accredited entity for a particular profession.</text>
    <text><strong>Classification Salary Adjustment </strong>– The movement of a classification to a different salary range due to changes in the labor supply, market conditions or due to a change in the duties and responsibilities associated with the classification.</text>
    <text><strong>Competitive Salary Offer</strong> – A counter offer to a higher salary offered by an organization outside of the City or another City agency to an employee deemed critical to the agency's mission and operations.</text>
    <text><strong>Demotion (Voluntary)</strong> – An employee initiated movement to a different classification in a lower salary range.</text>
    <text><strong>Demotion (Involuntary)</strong> – A management initiated movement of an employee to a different classification with a lower salary range for disciplinary or performance reasons.</text>
    <text><strong>Duties and Responsibilities</strong> - The primary and essential task assigned to a particular position or classification.</text>
    <text><strong>In-Range Adjustment ("IRA")</strong> – An increase to an employee's base pay on the basis of changes in duties and responsibilities, professional/skill development, or internal salary alignment.</text>
    <text><strong>Internal Salary Alignment</strong> – An increase to an employee's base pay based upon a comparison to the base pay of other employees within the agency who have comparable levels of training and experience, duties and responsibilities, similar performance and competencies, and/or knowledge and skills.</text>
    <text><strong>Lateral Transfer</strong> – The movement of an employee to a different position in the same classification or salary range.</text>
    <text><strong>License</strong> – A credential that is required by law to perform the duties of the position or classification.</text>
    <text><strong>Managerial and Professional Society of Baltimore, Inc. ("MAPS")</strong> – The representative organization for professional and supervisory employees of the City of Baltimore.</text>
    <text><strong>MAPS Performance Management Program</strong> – A program designed to improve organizational effectiveness by setting performance objectives, providing guidance and feedback, encouraging opportunities for professional development, and rewarding achievement.</text>
    <text><strong>Market Availability</strong> – The availability of suitable, qualified candidates in the general labor market that is subject to the changes in supply and demand.</text>
    <text><strong>Position Reclassification</strong> – A movement of a position to a different classification in a higher, (Upward Classification Change), lower (Downward Classification Change), or the same (Lateral Classification Change) salary range.</text>
    <text><strong>Performance</strong> – A measure of an employee's work accomplishments, outcomes and behavioral inter-actions assessed as part of the MAPS Performance Management Program.</text>
    <text><strong>Promotion</strong> – The advancement of an employee to a different classification with a higher maximum salary range through either reclassification of the employee's existing position or appointment of the employee to another position.</text>
    <text><strong>Salary Administration</strong> - The guidelines for establishing and changing compensation including Starting Pay, Promotion, Transfer, Demotion, Classification Change, In-Range Adjustment, Disciplinary Action, Performance-Related Salary Actions, and Competitive Offers.</text>
    <text><strong>Salary Grade</strong> - The three (3) digit number in the City's Human Resources Information System (HRIS) that is used to designate a specific salary range in the City's Salary Administration Plan for MAPS employees.</text>
    <text><strong>Salary Range</strong>- The minimum, mid-point, and maximum salary assigned to a classification for purposes of recruitment, and compensation administration.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="salary-administration">
    <num>III.</num>
    <heading>SALARY ADMINISTRATION</heading>
    <text>All MAPS positions shall be assigned to a Civil Service or Non-Civil Service classification with a specified salary range.  The salary range represents the minimum, mid-point, and maximum pay for the classification.  MAPS employees shall not be paid less than the minimum or more than the maximum of the assigned salary range for the classification.</text>
    <text>All salary decisions must be documented, and kept in the employee's personnel file throughout the employee's term of employment with the City and in accordance with applicable laws after the employee's separation from City services.</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <heading>Initial Appointment</heading>
      <text>Upon initial appointment, an employee shall be paid at least the minimum salary of the salary range to which the employee has been appointed.  An Agency may negotiate a starting base pay up to the mid-point of the assigned salary range.  An Agency shall not offer a candidate a starting base pay that exceeds the mid-point of the assigned salary range.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <heading>Promotion</heading>
      <text>When an employee is moved to a position in a different classification that has a higher maximum salary range, the employee's base pay shall be increased to either the minimum of the new salary range, or ten percent (10%) above the employee's current base pay, whichever is greater, not to exceed the maximum of the salary range for the new classification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <heading>Demotion</heading>
      <text>An employee may be demoted either voluntarily or involuntarily.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Voluntary</heading>
        <text>An employee who voluntarily moves to a position in a classification with a lower maximum salary shall retain their base pay unless their base pay exceeds the maximum salary of the lower classification.  In cases where the employee's base pay exceeds the maximum salary range for the lower classification the employee's base pay shall be reduced to the maximum salary of the lower classification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Involuntary</heading>
        <text>An employee may be demoted involuntarily for poor performance or disciplinary reasons.  The involuntary demotion may result in an employee moving to a position in a classification with a lower maximum salary or to a position in a classification with the same maximum salary.  The employees' base pay shall be reduced by a minimum of five percent (5%) unless the employee's reduced salary exceeds the maximum salary for the classification.  In cases where the employees' reduced base pay exceeds the maximum salary of the employee's classification the salary shall be reduced to the maximum salary of the lower classification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <heading>Lateral Transfer</heading>
      <text>An employee who transfers to a different position with the same salary range may negotiate the base pay for the new position up to ten percent (10%) above the employee's current base pay, not to exceed the maximum salary of the salary range for the classification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <heading>In-Range Adjustment</heading>
      <text>An Agency may initiate an In-Range Adjustment to resolve specific salary issues or provide potential salary growth and career progression within a salary range.  An In-Range Adjustment shall not exceed an increase of five percent (5%) of the employee's base pay.  An employee may receive more than one In-Range Adjustment in a fiscal year provided that the total of all In-Range Adjustments does not exceed five percent (5%) during the fiscal year.  An employee shall be ineligible for an In-Range Adjustment if the employee's base pay is at the maximum of the salary range.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Permanent Change In Duties</heading>
        <text>An increase in base pay may be granted to an employee who assumes new higher-level duties and responsibilities on a permanent basis that are critical to the operations of an agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Internal Alignment</heading>
        <text>An increase in base pay may be granted to align an employee's salary with those of other employees' within the same agency who have comparable levels of training and experience, similar duties and responsibilities, performance, competencies and/or knowledge and skills.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Professional/Skill Development</heading>
        <text>An employee may receive an increase in base pay for completing a course of study directly related to the duties and responsibilities of the employee's position.</text>
        <text>
          <strong>All In-Range Adjustments are discretionary actions, based upon the availability of funds and the prior approval of the Director of DHR.</strong>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <heading>Performance Based Salary Increases</heading>
      <text>An Agency may propose a base pay increase for employees performing at or above the satisfactory level as defined in the MAPS Performance Management Program and Policy.  Performance based increases shall not cause an employee's base pay to exceed the maximum salary of the employee's current salary range.</text>
      <text>
        <strong>All performance based increases are discretionary, based upon the availability of funds and require the prior approval of the Director of DHR.</strong>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <heading>Competitive Offer</heading>
      <text>An Agency may provide a salary adjustment to an employee who is deemed critical to the agency's mission and on-going operations when the employee receives a job offer from another City agency (Internal Competitive Salary Offer), or from outside of City government (External Competitive Salary Offer).  A competitive offer may not occur within an agency.  When providing competitive salary adjustments, agencies must comply with the following guidelines:</text>
      <text class="text-indent-1">
        <ul>
          <li>Obtain a copy of the written offer for verification</li>
          <li>Assess the need to retain the employee, the impact on agency operations if the employee separates and the difficulty in recruiting to replace the employee</li>
          <li>Request approval from the Director of Human Resources prior to extending a competitive salary offer</li>
        </ul>
      </text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Internal Competitive Salary Offer</heading>
        <text class="text-indent-1">
          <ul>
            <li>When an employee receives a higher salary offer from another City agency, there can be only one counter-offer from the employee's current agency.</li>
            <li>The amount of the counter-offer may not exceed the amount of the job offer from the other agency.</li>
            <li>The other City agency may not make a second offer in response to the current agency's counter-offer.</li>
          </ul>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>External Competitive Salary Offer</heading>
        <text>When an employee receives a salary offer from an organization external to the City, the employing agency may make a counter-offer, not to exceed the amount of the job offer, or a 10% increase over the employee's current base pay, whichever is less, not to exceed the maximum salary of the assigned salary range.</text>
        <text>
          <strong>All competitive salary offers are discretionary, subject to the availability of funds and require the prior approval of the Director of DHR.</strong>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <heading>Temporary Assignment</heading>
      <text>An employee may be temporarily assigned additional duties and responsibilities as a result of agency needs or a special project.  The Agency shall obtain approval from the Director of Human Resources, prior to an employee beginning a temporary assignment, by submitting a request for study of the additional duties and responsibilities.  Employees approved for temporary assignment shall receive five percent (5%) of the employee's base pay as additional compensation for the term of the temporary assignment only.  Temporary assignments are limited to an initial four month period with an option for the agency to extend for two additional four month periods, not to exceed one year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <heading>Position Reclassification</heading>
      <text>A position may be changed to a different classification in a higher, lower or the same salary range due to a change in the duties and responsibilities of the position or as a result of a classification study.  A position reclassification does not result in a change in position number.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Upward Classification Change</heading>
        <text>The employee's classification and base pay remain unchanged, until a Promotion is processed in accordance with the provisions of Section III(B).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Downward Classification Change</heading>
        <text>An employee whose position has been reclassified to a lower salary range will have their base pay adjusted according to the City's Downgrading Policy, <cite path="§AM-230-5">AM-230-5</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Lateral Classification Change</heading>
        <text>The employee's base pay shall not be changed when a position is changed to a different classification in the same salary range.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <heading>Classification Salary Adjustment</heading>
      <text>Agencies may submit a request to the Director of Human Resources for the movement of a classification to a different salary range or DHR may initiate a study that results in the movement of a classification to a different salary range.  When the salary range for a classification is changed, the employee's base pay remains unchanged provided the employee's current base pay is within the new salary range.</text>
      <text>When a classification is moved to a higher salary range and the employee's current base pay is below the minimum salary of the new range, the employee's base pay will be adjusted to the minimum of the higher salary range.</text>
      <text>When a classification is moved to a lower salary range and the employee's current base pay is above the maximum salary of the new range, the employee's base pay will be adjusted to the maximum salary of the lower salary range.</text>
    </para>
  </para>
  <para name="return-to-city-service">
    <num>IV.</num>
    <heading>RETURN TO CITY SERVICE</heading>
    <text>All former employees returning to City service in a MAPS classification will have their base pay established according to the Starting Pay provisions of this policy.</text>
    <para>
      <num>1.</num>
      <heading>Military Leave</heading>
      <text>An employee returning to City service after time off for military service will have their base pay established according the provisions of <cite path="§AM-204-11">AM-204-11</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>2.</num>
      <heading>Layoff</heading>
      <text>A former employee rehired within one (1) year of the layoff will have their base pay established as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>i.</num>
        <text>If the employee is rehired into the same classification, the employee's base pay will be the same as the base pay the employee would have been entitled to if the layoff had not occurred.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>ii.</num>
        <text>If the employee is rehired in a classification with a lower salary range than the classification the employee held at the time of the layoff, the employee's base pay will be the same as in 2(i), unless the base pay is above the maximum of the lower salary range.  When the employee's base pay exceeds the maximum of the lower salary range, the employee's base pay shall be reduced to the maximum salary of the range.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>iii.</num>
        <text>If the employee is rehired into a classification with a higher salary range than the classification the employee held at the time of the layoff, the employee's base pay will be the same as in 2(i), unless the base pay is below the minimum of the higher salary range.  When the employee's base pay is lower the minimum of the lower salary range, the employee's base pay shall be increased to the minimum salary of the range.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>3.</num>
      <heading>Reinstatement</heading>
      <text>A former employee reinstated to a position in the same classification within one (1) year of the employee's voluntary resignation will receive the same base pay the employee was receiving at the time of their resignation.  Former employees must meet all criteria for reinstatement as set forth in <cite path="§AM-213-1, Part I">AM-213-1, Part I</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>4.</num>
      <heading>Subsequent Employment</heading>
      <text>A former employee obtaining subsequent employment with the City in a different classification within one (1) year of the employee's voluntary resignation will have their base pay established in accordance with the Initial Appointment provisions of this policy.</text>
    </para>
  </para>
  <para name="exceptions">
    <num>V.</num>
    <heading>EXCEPTIONS</heading>
    <text>The Director of Human Resources has the authority to grant an exception to any provisions of this policy.  To request an exception, the agency shall complete and submit <u>MAPS Salary Policy Exception Form</u> (<strong><cite path="§AM-205-20-1">AM-205-20-1</cite></strong>) providing all necessary information including a detailed justification of the need for the exception.  All exceptions are within the sole discretion of the Director of Human Resources and subject to the availability of funds.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="authority">
    <num>VI.</num>
    <heading>AUTHORITY</heading>
    <text>The Department of Human Resources issues this policy pursuant to the authority provided in <cite doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Charter">the City Charter</cite>, Articles VI and VII, and the approval of the City's Board of Estimates.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="interpretation">
    <num>VII.</num>
    <heading>INTERPRETATION</heading>
    <text>The Director of Human Resources is responsible for the official interpretation of this policy.</text>
    <text>The Department of Human Resources reserves the right to revise or eliminate this policy at any time, with the approval of the City's Board of Estimates.</text>
  </para>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" display="true" effective="2014-07-01">July 1, 2014</annotation>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM 200-5" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM 204-11" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM 204-30" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM 204-31" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM 205-8" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM 205-9" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM 213-1|1" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM 213-1|II" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM 213-1-1" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM 230-4" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM 230-5" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM 235-1" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM 290-07" type="Related Policies"/>
  </annotations>
</section>
