<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-227-2</num>
  <heading>Prohibition of Weapons in the Workplace</heading>
  <text>The City of Baltimore ("City") is committed to maintaining a work environment that is safe for individuals working for the City and its citizens.  To achieve this objective, the City is committed to taking a strong stand against firearms and weapons in the workplace by strictly enforcing this Policy.</text>
  <para name="purpose">
    <num>I.</num>
    <heading>PURPOSE</heading>
    <text>To promote a safe and incident-free environment for individuals working for the City, citizens, and visitors, and to maintain a workplace free from firearms and dangerous weapons, the City prohibits the possession, use, or sale of weapons, firearms, or explosives while on City-owned or leased property; while operating City machinery, equipment or vehicles; or while engaged in City business off premises, including circumstances where an individual may have a valid license or permit authorizing him/her to carry a firearm, unless expressly authorized by the City and/or required by federal, state, and local law.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="scope">
    <num>II.</num>
    <heading>SCOPE</heading>
    <text>This Policy applies to all individuals working for the City, including full and part-time employees, contractual employees, volunteers, interns, independent contractors, staffing agency workers, and any other person(s), whether or not compensated, who perform work on behalf of the City or on City-owned or leased property.  This Policy also applies to individuals who conduct business on City-owned or leased property and visitors of such premises.  Further, this Policy applies to individuals who have a valid permit to carry a firearm.</text>
    <text>The City recognizes that many job classifications in the City require the use of certain equipment/tools for employees occupying positions in those classifications to carry out the functions of their positions.  This Policy exempts work-issued and work-authorized equipment from coverage, except where they are used for non-permitted/non-work related purposes, such as causing bodily harm to others or the destruction of property.</text>
    <text>Sworn members of the Baltimore City Police Department ("BCFD") and any other individuals expressly authorized by the City and/or required by federal, state or local law to carry a firearm, weapon, or explosive are excluded from the application of this Policy.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="definitions">
    <num>III.</num>
    <heading>DEFINITIONS</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <heading>City Event:</heading>
      <text>Any occasion (concert, street fair, etc.) that is sponsored or co-sponsored by the City.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <heading>City Property:</heading>
      <text>All property owned or leased by the City, including machinery, equipment, vehicles, parking lots, garages, and yards.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <heading>Firearm, Weapon and Explosive:</heading>
      <text>For purposes of this Policy, the terms "firearm" "weapon" and "explosive" include, but are not limited to the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Handguns, pistols, revolvers, shotguns, rifles, b-b guns, or other loaded or unloaded weapons from which a projectile may be discharged by means of gas, compressed air, or explosives;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Any device designed as a weapon and capable of bodily harm, such as stun guns, Tasers, hunting knives, switch blades, brass knuckles, nun chucks, sling shots, pepper spray, and other similar weapons;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Combustible or flammable liquids or noxious fumes, and chemicals intended to be used as weapons;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>Bombs, Molotov cocktails, fireworks, dynamite, and other types of explosive devices; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>Items not designed to cause injury but are intended by the user to cause apprehension of imminent bodily injury.  Examples of such items include but are not limited to eating utensils, work equipment, scissors, and pens.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <heading>Work Site or Workplace:</heading>
      <text>Any location whether owned or leased by the City or any other location not owned or leased by the City where a City employee, vendor, contractor, agent, temporary worker, or volunteer is carrying out the responsibilities and duties of his/her job on behalf of the City.</text>
    </para>
  </para>
  <para name="prohibited-conduct">
    <num>IV.</num>
    <heading>PROHIBITED CONDUCT</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The possession or transportation of firearms, weapons, or explosives are strictly prohibited in City vehicles and includes, but not limited to: (1) traveling to and from work; (2) when conducting City business; and (3) at all times in City-owned or leased vehicles, machinery and equipment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The possession of firearms (even under circumstances where the person has a permit to carry a firearm), weapons, or explosives while on City Property or at a City Event is strictly prohibited.</text>
    </para>
  </para>
  <para name="responsibilities">
    <num>V.</num>
    <heading>RESPONSIBILITIES</heading>
    <text>The safety, welfare, and well-being of City employees, visitors, and persons conducting business with or on behalf of the City are the principle concerns of this Policy.  No person should ever jeopardize his/her own safety or that of others when observing this Policy.  It is therefore required that no one attempt to disarm any person in possession of a firearm, weapon, or explosive. Instead, any such violations should be reported to a supervisor or where there is a possible threat of bodily harm, notify the BCPD by dialing 9-1-1.</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <heading>Employees.</heading>
      <text>It is the responsibility of each employee to seek clarification as to whether an item or instrument is deemed a firearm or dangerous weapon prior to bringing the item or instrument onto City Property or a City Event.  Employees seeking clarification should contact their immediate supervisor or, where applicable, building security prior to bringing the item onto City Property or a City Event.  Employees are encouraged to report violations of this Policy to their supervisor or their Agency Human Resources Practitioner.  When there is a possible threat of bodily injury, 9-1-1 should be called immediately.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <heading>Supervisors and Managers.</heading>
      <text>All supervisors and managers who become aware of any person violating this Policy shall immediately notify the Agency Human Resources Practitioner, his/her immediate supervisor, and/or the BCPD, where applicable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <heading>Agency Human Resources Practitioners.</heading>
      <text>Agency Human Resources Practitioners shall immediately notify the Agency Head of any violation of this Policy, regardless of whether the violation is committed by an employee, a visitor, or a person conducting business with the City or on the City's behalf.  Agency Human Resources Practitioners are responsible for ensuring that each employee completes a statement acknowledging receipt and understanding of this Policy.  It is also the responsibility of the Agency Human Resources Practitioners to ensure that a copy of this Policy is conspicuously posted in a central area of the workplace and visible to employees, visitors, and persons conducting business with or on behalf of the City.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <heading>Agency Head.</heading>
      <text>The Agency Head, or designee, is generally responsible for enforcing this Policy and administering discipline for violations of this Policy up to, and including, termination.</text>
    </para>
  </para>
  <para name="consequences-for-violations">
    <num>VI.</num>
    <heading>CONSEQUENCES FOR VIOLATIONS</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any individual working for the City found in violation of this Policy is subject to disciplinary action up to and including termination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Any person not working for the City who violates this Policy will be removed immediately from City property and his/her conduct will be reported to the proper authorities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Possession of a weapons permit authorized by the State of Maryland is not an exemption under this Policy.</text>
    </para>
  </para>
  <para name="authority">
    <num>VII.</num>
    <heading>AUTHORITY</heading>
    <text>This Policy was issued pursuant to <em><cite path="§AM-002-1">AM-002-1</cite></em> and <em>002-1-2 Administrative Manual</em> wherein the Department of Human Resources recommended changes to the Administrative Manual to the Board of Estimates for approval.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="interpretation">
    <num>VIII.</num>
    <heading>INTERPRETATION</heading>
    <text>The Department of Human Resources reserves the right to revise or eliminate this Policy at any time. The City's Board of Estimates reserves the right to approve proposed policy revisions or eliminations as determined by the Department of Human Resources.</text>
  </para>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" effective="2017-12-13" display="true">December 13, 2017</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-227-1">AM-227-1</cite> Workplace Violence Policy</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-227-1-1">AM-227-1-1</cite> Procedures for Avoiding Physical Attack</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-227-1-2">AM-227-1-2</cite> Workplace Violence Incident Report</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-227-1-3">AM-227-1-3</cite> Memo – Protective Order Notification</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-227-1-4">AM-227-1-4</cite> Memo Sample – Performance Improvement Plan</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-227-1-5">AM-227-1-5</cite> Acknowledgement of Workplace Violence Policy</annotation>
  </annotations>
</section>
