<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-303-4</num>
  <heading>Informal Bids</heading>
  <para name="scope">
    <heading>SCOPE</heading>
    <text>An informal bid involves the procurement of any supplies, materials, equipment or services, other than food or professional services, which have a value of less than $25,000. In cases of a food bid, the procurement must be less than $40,000. Bids are opened at 11:00 a.m. on the specified due date during the workweek; however there are no informal bid openings on Wednesday. Recommended bids are submitted to the Board of Estimates for award, except for bid awards of less than $5,000, which are awarded by the Department of Finance, Bureau of Purchases or the responsible City department.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="delivery-of-bids">
    <heading>DELIVERY OF BIDS</heading>
    <text>The Informal Bid Office is located in Department of Finance, Bureau of Purchases, 231 E. Baltimore St., Suite 200, Baltimore, MD 21202. The office is open from 8:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m., five days a week. Vendors may deliver sealed bids only to this office on any day before the bid due date, but no later than 11:00 a.m. on the due date.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="bid-deadline">
    <heading>BID DEADLINE</heading>
    <text>The bid office personnel accepts no responsibility for a vendor's failure to meet the deadline of a specified bid opening. All informal bids must be accepted and stamped before 11:01 a.m. on the bid due date. Any bid received after 11:01 a.m. will be marked "late" and returned with the original bid envelope to the vendor with the appropriate explanatory letter. A copy of the bid envelope and explanatory letter are forwarded to the Bureau of Purchases or the responsible City department along with all acceptable bids for award consideration. The time stamp clock is set daily by calling local time on 410-844-1212 and is the official time for determining whether a bid has been submitted by the deadline.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="opening-of-bids">
    <heading>OPENING OF BIDS</heading>
    <text>Vendor informal bids are opened at the Informal Bid Office, processed, stored in computerized archives, and then dispersed. The originals are then sent to the Bureau of Purchases or appropriate City department for evaluation and award. Results of bid openings, which are in computerized archives, may be reviewed no earlier than the following Tuesday of the bid opening date at the Bureau of Purchases, 231 E. Baltimore St., Suite 200.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="public-reading-of-bids">
    <heading>PUBLIC READING OF BIDS</heading>
    <text>The purpose of the public reading on an informal bid is to permit any interested party to observe the opening of the informal bid envelopes by bid office personnel. Also, at the public reading a vendor may request the reading of prices for the solicitation in which they are interested. An informal bid public reading takes place immediately following the 11:00 a.m. deadline on the due date. A maximum of 10 items will be read from each bid list, if requested. A vendor is not permitted to read, to inspect or to handle an informal bid at anytime. Personnel of this office are not permitted to give information over the telephone in reference to bid results.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="transmission-of-bids">
    <heading>TRANSMISSION OF BIDS</heading>
    <text>Bids are transmitted to the awarding department or the Bureau of Purchases within two (2) days after the bid opening.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="formal-bids">
    <heading>FORMAL BIDS</heading>
    <text>The Informal Bid Office is not authorized to process "Formal Bids". Personnel of the informal bid office are not authorized to provide information to buyers or vendors on "Formal Bids". Formal Bids are received in Room 204, City Hall, 100 N. Holliday St. and are the responsibility of the Office of the Comptroller.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="extension-of-due-date">
    <heading>EXTENSION OF DUE DATE</heading>
    <text>The due date of an informal bid may be changed by the Bureau of Purchases or the awarding department, provided that the Informal Bid Office is informed in writing by the City Purchasing Agent or awarding department of the change before the due date of the bid. The Bureau of Purchases or the awarding department accepts responsibility for informing all affected vendors.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="rejection-of-bids">
    <heading>REJECTION OF BIDS</heading>
    <text>If an informal bid contains a submission entry in pencil, the entire bid will be rejected. An informal bid with insufficient postage affixed to it will be refused by the Bid Office personnel. All informal bids received after the public deadline will also be rejected. An informal bid submitted by Facsimile or e-mail will be rejected. Bids that are not delivered in sealed envelopes will not be accepted.</text>
  </para>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" effective="1988-06-15" display="true">June 15, 1988</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" effective="2001-01-01" display="true">January 1, 2001</annotation>
  </annotations>
</section>
