<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>PUBLIC TRAFFIC CALMING REQUESTS</heading>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Baltimore City Code, Article 31, §§2-2 and 2-5.</annotation>
    <annotation type="Editor's Notes" dest="container">The attached regulations have been submitted to the Director of the Department of Legislative Reference for COBRA codification in accordance with <cite doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Code" path="|general|4|4|4-401">§ 4-401, Title 4 { Administrative Procedure Act – Regulations }</cite> of the <cite doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Code" path="|general">General Provisions Article of the Baltimore City Code</cite>. The attached regulations have not been reviewed by the Department of Legislative Reference for adherence to COBRA formatting and are subject to non-substantive formatting changes. Published by Baltimore City Department of Legislative Reference Avery Aisenstark, Director 2022 Copyright © 2022 The Mayor and City Council of Baltimore Department of Legislative Reference All rights reserved For Information: Department of Legislative Reference City Hall 100 N. Holliday Street, Suite 626 Baltimore, Maryland 21202 Tel: (410) 396-4730 https://legislativereference.baltimorecity.gov/ </annotation>
  </annotations>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>These regulations:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>Implement a plan for fulfilling public service requests for traffic calming through the 311-system in Baltimore City;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>Create a prioritization system for traffic calming that accounts for equity; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>Expand the toolkit of traffic calming options to promote safety and livability on City streets.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In <cite path="14.09.01">this chapter</cite>, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Arterial street" means freeways, multilane highways, and other important roadways that supplement the United States Interstate System.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"BCDOT" refers to the Baltimore City Department of Transportation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Collector street" means major and minor roads that connect local roads and streets with arterials.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Complete Streets" means a program in Baltimore City that enables access, mobility, economic development, attractive public spaces, health, and well-being for all people.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Corridor" means the roadway and adjacent affected roadways where traffic calming is requested.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Equity Priority Zones" means equity zones defined by the Complete Streets Manual.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Local or neighborhood street" means roads that service limited vehicular traffic and are the primary access to residential areas, neighborhoods, and other local areas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Neighborhood" means community identified by the Baltimore City Planning Department's official "Neighborhood Statistical Area Map".</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Prioritization process" means procedure by which streets or corridors are selected and ranked for traffic calming projects.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Service Request (SR)" or "311 Service Request" means a request made via phone or online to the Baltimore City 311 System.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Stakeholder" means individuals or entities that are affected by <cite path="14.09.01.02">this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Traffic Calming" means devices or methods used to slow the speed of traffic or reduce volume of traffic.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Initiation of the Traffic Calming Process.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Arterial streets are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>not subject to the requirements for local or collector streets; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>subject to a separate investigation process for alternative traffic calming measures.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A stakeholder requesting traffic calming in a neighborhood on a local or collector street shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>live within the neighborhood;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>own or operate a business within the neighborhood;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>represent a school or daycare facility within the neighborhood;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>represent a Community Organization within the neighborhood; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>be a public, elected official, or his or her designee, whose district's boundaries are within or include a portion of the City of Baltimore.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To initiate the traffic calming process, the Stakeholder must complete a 311 Service Request by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>calling 311; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>filling out an online survey</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>through the mobile phone application for 311 Service Requests; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>on City of Baltimore's 311 website.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A Stakeholder shall provide the following information to be considered for a traffic calming request:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>legal first and last name;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>email address or phone number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>street address;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>start and end points of the roadway segments where the need for traffic calming should be investigated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>a specific address or location where speed or cut-through traffic are of concern;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>any relevant and necessary information regarding the traffic calming service request.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>For BCDOT to consider a Service Request, the Stakeholder must provide the information found in <cite path="14.09.01.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite> in full.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>After submission, the stakeholder will be given:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>a time period for receiving an update for the service request;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>the service request number; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>if using online or mobile application, a confirmation email with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A copy of the completed service request form; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The information listed above in <cite path="14.09.01.03|D.">Regulation .03.D</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Investigation of Traffic Calming Request.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The BCDOT shall</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>evaluate the need and feasibility of traffic calming, and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>simultaneously provide the Service Request to the Baltimore City Fire Department for notification and feedback.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Data collection and analysis shall proceed immediately following the BCDOT determination of a valid request for traffic calming.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Data Collection and Analysis.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>BCDOT Traffic Division shall collect data within the study corridor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The information collected will be analyzed by BCDOT to determine if traffic calming is</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>warranted, and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>feasible.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Data collection units may be deployed on site to collect data related to speed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Data collection units shall be deployed based on engineering judgement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A site visit may be conducted to document conditions including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>roadway grade;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>roadway width and cross-section;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>roadway horizontal geometry;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>lane configurations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>adjacent land-use;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>multimodal traffic operations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>other related geometric and operational roadway features.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The following elements may be reviewed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>crash data over the previous 6 years;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>street type and target speed in accordance with the Baltimore Complete Streets Manual; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Equity Priority Zones.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Local and collector roadways with longitudinal grades of 8 percent or lower that meet the traffic calming criteria for need and feasibility can proceed to the prioritization process.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Local or collector roadways with longitudinal grades greater than 8 percent require further engineering review to determine the applicability and feasibility of</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>traffic calming, or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>other mitigation measures:</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Prioritization Process.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Following data collection, and approval, BCDOT shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Move the traffic calming Service Request forward to the prioritization process; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit the Service Request for further engineering or review by Baltimore City Fire Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the application does not meet the criteria threshold of the data collection and analysis, BCDOT shall issue a statement to the Stakeholder denying the Service Request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>BCDOT shall prioritize traffic calming requests based on:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Severity and prevalence of speeding based on initial data investigation and historical data;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Severity and prevalence of crashes based on historical data;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The presence of school zones; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Equity Zones as identified on BCDOT's Equity Map.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Prior to the beginning of construction season, the prioritization process will determine the construction program on an annual basis.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Community Involvement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Prior to implementation of traffic calming measures, BCDOT shall notify stakeholders of the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A summary of the traffic calming plan;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The timeframe of the project comment period; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Contact information pertaining to comments or an opt-out request.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>BCDOT shall notify stakeholders by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Postcard or letter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Electronic communication;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Social media; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Other community outreach methods.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>BCDOT may post signs on the street in question with the information above.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The following conditions apply to opt-out requests:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Only opt-out requests from stakeholders abutting the immediate project block(s) shall be considered;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Stakeholders may be required to provide proof of residency when opting out;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Comments must be submitted within the specified response period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Construction Scheduling</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon conclusion of the public comment period and pending funding availability, BCDOT will schedule the traffic calming devices or measures for installation using the location's score from the prioritization process.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Local and collector streets that are approved for the installation of traffic calming measures will be scheduled for construction on an annual basis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Arterial streets may be scheduled for construction separately from local and collector streets to allow for additional analysis, more comprehensive treatments, or other factors.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Review</heading>
    <text>After installation of traffic calming devices, BCDOT may review traffic calming devices for effectiveness.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Traffic Calming Devices</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Types and descriptions of traffic calming devices are available for review within the Design Guidance section of the Baltimore Complete Streets Manual.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Options for traffic calming devices include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>speed humps, speed tables, and speed cushions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>curb extensions, also known as bump-outs or bulb-outs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>rumble strips;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>hardened centerline treatments;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>raised crosswalks;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>raised intersections;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>chicanes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>mini-roundabouts, also known as neighborhood traffic circles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>traffic signal timing and operations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>vehicle access restrictions, such as median diverters;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>traffic signal timing and operations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>reduction in travelway width;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>reduction in number of through or travel lanes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Slow Streets treatments;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>any combination of these devices;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>other available treatments or devices.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
</container>
