<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="City of Balt., Md., Res. 24-318" codify:doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Charter">
  <num type="law">24-318</num>
  <num type="bill">23-0444</num>
  <heading type="short">Charter Amendment – Inner Harbor Park</heading>
  <heading type="long">A Resolution of the Mayor and City Council Concerning Charter Amendment – Inner Harbor Park</heading>
  <meta>
    <stub/>
    <effective>2024-11-05</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/24-318.pdf">Res. 24-318</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <vote date="2024-02-26" reading="second"/>
      <adopted>2024-11-05</adopted>
      <committee>Favorable, as amended</committee>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section>
    <prefix>Section</prefix>
    <num>1</num>
    <codify:replace path="I|§9" codified:doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Charter" codified:path="I|§9">
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>9</num>
        <heading>Inner Harbor Park.</heading>
        <text>There is hereby dedicated to public park uses for the benefit of this and future generations of the City of Baltimore and the State of Maryland the portion of the City that lies along the north, west and south shores of the Inner Harbor, south of Pratt Street to the water's edge, east of Light Street to the water's edge and north of Key Highway to the water's edge, from the World Trade Center around the shoreline of the Inner Harbor to and including Rash Field, except that, in order to provide multi-family dwellings and off-street parking, eating places and other commercial uses, areas totalling not more than 4.5 acres plus access thereto, within the dedicated space and north of an easterly extension of the south side of Conway Street shall be set aside for such purposes, except that any areas used for multi-family dwellings and off-street parking are not dedicated as a public park; and except that in order to provide outdoor eating places for the areas known as West Shore Park and Rash Field, areas totalling not more than 0.5 acres within the dedicated space and south of an easterly extension of the south side of Conway Street shall be set aside for such purposes; and except that an area of not more than 3.4 acres shall be set aside for use by the Maryland Science Center, plus access thereto.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Editor's Notes">
            <text>Ordinance 24-318, known as Ballot Question F, which was ratified on November 5, 2024, enlarged the permitted acreage for development within Inner Harbor Park from 3.2 to 4.5 acres. In addition, the Ordinance added multi-family dwellings and off-street parking to the list of permitted uses within this development space, but any land occupied by those two uses would no longer be part of the public park. Section 2 of the Ordinance states "[t]hat in enacting this Resolution of the Mayor and City Council, it is the intent of the Mayor and City Council to preserve the public park known as Rash Field and to preserve the existing development restrictions within the Inner Harbor Park south of Conway Street."</text>
            <text><strong>Litigation related to Ballot Question F.</strong> A group of 23 Baltimore City voters filed a petition for judicial review of Ballot Question F in the Circuit Court for Anne Arundel County alleging that Ballot Question F was invalid because (1) it was improper "charter material" in violation of Article XI-A, § 3 of the Constitution of Maryland and (2) the language of the question was not "easily understandable by voters" in violation of § 9-203(1) of the State Election Law Article, in addition to other claims. After the circuit court found that the measure could be included on the ballot but the votes for or against it could not be certified, the decision was appealed to the Maryland Supreme Court. The Supreme Court of Maryland issued a per curium order dated October 10, 2024, permitting the votes for or against Question F to be counted and certified.</text>
          </annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </codify:replace>
  </section>
</document>
