<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>FIXED PRICING PROGRAM</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text><cite path="07.03.03">This chapter</cite> establishes regulations governing the Fixed Pricing Program including:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Application requirements;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Review criteria;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Approval criteria;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Applicant responsibilities; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Departmental responsibilities.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Exclusions.</heading>
    <text>The Department may not list a property for sale through the Fixed Pricing Program if the property:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Is valued over $100,000;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Is identified for site assemblage;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Is part of an existing development project; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Is needed to implement a Departmental whole block strategy.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Property Types.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department may sell a property through the Fixed Pricing Program if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The property is listed as available on the City's BuyIntoBmore webpage;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The property is located within a housing market typology category approved for sale in the Fixed Pricing Policy; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The property will be redeveloped for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Residential use;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Residential mixed-use; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Green space.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Homeowner Side Yard.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department may sell a property through the Fixed Pricing Program for use as a side yard if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The property is a vacant lot;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The property is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Adjacent to an occupied lot; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Being sold as for use as a side yard to the owner of the occupied lot; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The property is located in housing market typologies A-J.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department shall ensure a property sold as homeowner side yard remains subject to a 3-year use restriction that prohibits new construction during that period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Price.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In General.</text>
      <text>The Department shall sell a property through the Fixed Pricing Program at the price established in the approved Fixed Pricing Policy and required by these regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Fixed Price Established for Vacant Buildings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A developer shall pay $3000.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A large 501(c)(3) nonprofit shall pay $3000.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A small 501(c)(3) nonprofit shall pay $1000.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A community land trust shall pay $1.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A homeowner shall pay $1.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Fixed Price Established for Vacant Lots.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A developer shall pay $1000.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A large 501(c)(3) nonprofit shall pay $1000.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A small 501(c)(3) nonprofit shall pay $500.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A community land trust shall pay $1.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A homeowner shall pay $1.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a property is assessed for less than the fixed price established in <cite path="07.03.03.04">this regulation</cite>, then the Department shall sell the property at the value assessed.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Applicant Specific Requirements – Developers and Nonprofits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following applicant types will be subject to <cite path="07.03.03.05">this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A developer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A 501(c)(3) nonprofit, including a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Small 501(c)(3) nonprofit; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Large 501(c)(3) nonprofit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant type provided for in <cite path="07.03.03.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall ensure:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A vacant building acquired through the Fixed Pricing Program is developed for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Residential use;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Residential mixed-use; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Residential mixed-use that includes a green space; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An occupancy permit is obtained within 12 months from the date of settlement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Applicant Specific Requirements – Affordable Housing Land Trusts.</heading>
    <text>An affordable housing land trust applying to the Fixed Pricing Program shall ensure that the affordable housing land trusts are:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Registered as an affordable housing land trust with the Maryland State Department of Assessments and Taxation; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In compliance with applicable State affordable housing land trust laws.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Applicant Specific Requirements – Homeowners.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Vacant Buildings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A homeowner applying to purchase a vacant building through the Fixed Pricing Program shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Ensure an occupancy permit is obtained within 12 months from the date of settlement; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maintain primary residency at the property for a minimum of 5 years from the date of issuance of the occupancy permit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a property purchased by a homeowner for primary residency is sold or leased within the 6-year period, the homeowner shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Deemed to be a developer of the property; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Required to pay a pro-rated portion of $3,000 calculated based on the year that the property is sold.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Vacant Lots.</text>
      <text>A homeowner applying to purchase a vacant lot through the Fixed Pricing Program shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Construct a new residential unit and satisfy the requirements in <cite path="07.03.03.07|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ensure the lot is used as a side yard in accordance with <cite path="07.03.03.03|B.|(2)">§03(B)(2) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Property Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department may consider a property eligible for the Fixed Pricing Program if the property is assessed at less than $100,000.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Properties Assessed Over $100,000</text>
      <text>For a property assessed at over $100,000, the Department may perform an internal valuation to determine:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whether the property is eligible for the Fixed Pricing Program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A sale price for a property through the Fixed Pricing Program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the valuation determined under <cite path="07.03.03.08|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> finds the true value of the assessed property to be less than $100,000, the Department may consider the property eligible for sale under the Fixed Pricing Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the valuation determined under <cite path="07.03.03.08|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> finds the true value of the assessed property to be $100,000 or greater, the Department may not consider the property eligible under the Fixed Pricing Program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Applicant Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In General.</text>
      <text>To be eligible for the Fixed Pricing Program, an applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Possess financial documents indicating no less than the minimum amount required by the Department for application, per applicable property;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be in good standing with the State Department of Assessments and Taxation, if they are a business entity; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be free of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An open federal lien;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An open state lien; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An applicable legal matter, in accordance with <cite path="07.03.03.09|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Vacant Building Notices.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In addition to the requirements specified in <cite path="07.03.03.09|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the Department shall consider whether an applicant owns a building with a vacant building notice in determining eligibility for the Fixed Pricing Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department may determine an applicant to be ineligible if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The applicant possesses a vacant building notice older than 2 years; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The applicant possesses a vacant building notice that is less than 2 years old, but there are no open or active construction permits on the property.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Legal Matters.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pending Civil Proceedings.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Department shall assess whether an applicant has a pending civil proceeding during review of applicant eligibility, including a:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Pending federal judgement; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Pending State judgement.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Department may reject an applicant based on a pending civil proceeding if the Department determines that the pending legal proceeding could inhibit the applicant from:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Adhering to the terms of a land disposition agreement; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Financing a purchase.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If an applicant rejected in accordance with <cite path="07.03.03.09|C.|(2)">§(2) of this section</cite> has a pending civil proceeding dropped or resolved in their favor, the applicant may re-apply for the Fixed Pricing Program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Criminal Cases.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Department may reject an applicant based on a criminal case that could lead to imprisonment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If an applicant rejected in accordance with <cite path="07.03.03.09|C.|(2)|(a)">§(2)(a) of this section</cite> is found not guilty, the applicant may re-apply for the Fixed Pricing Program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Fixed Pricing Program - Applications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to the general application requirements for a disposition program listed in <cite path="07.03.02">chapter 02 of this subtitle</cite>, an applicant applying for the Fixed Pricing Program shall adhere to the requirements of <cite path="07.03.03.10">this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant applying for the Fixed Pricing Program may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Exceed 12 properties per application; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit multiple applications under different applicant names for more than 12 properties at a time.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant may apply for additional properties as use and occupancy permits on a previously purchased property are obtained in accordance with <cite path="07.03.03">this chapter</cite>, not to exceed 12 properties at any given time.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Side Yard Application.</text>
      <text>To apply to purchase a side yard through the Fixed Pricing Program, an applicant shall provide:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Documentation verifying that the applicant owns the property adjacent to the lot to be purchased for use as a side yard;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Documentation that the applicant's adjacent property has a confirmed use and occupancy permit; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Documentation of an approved Homestead Tax application through the State Department of Assessments and Taxation confirming use and primary residence of the applicant's adjacent property.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Approval.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall approve an application to the Fixed Pricing Program in accordance with <cite path="07.03.02">Chapter 02 of this subtitle</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Board of Estimates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit a list of the following items through the BOE portal:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The address of a property awarded through the Fixed Pricing Program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The purchase price of a property awarded through the Fixed Pricing Program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The contact information of the prospective purchaser; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The type of purchaser; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Post the list required by <cite path="07.03.03.12|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> on the Department's website the Monday prior to the next Board Meeting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board of Estimates shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maintain a recurring item on the Board meeting agenda titled "Fixed Pricing Policy Dispositions" to review the list provided by the Department in <cite path="07.03.03.12|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Consider a purchaser's inclusion on the agenda as an indication of the purchaser's approval of the terms of the land disposition agreement approved by the Board in accordance with <cite path="07.03.02">chapter 02 of this subtitle</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Land Disposition Agreement – Fixed Pricing Program.</heading>
    <text>In addition to the provisions of <cite path="07.03.02">chapter 02 of this subtitle</cite>:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department shall post an approved land disposition agreement executed for a Fixed Pricing Program disposition online for the purchaser to review.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department may not send a land disposition agreement executed for a Fixed Pricing Program disposition directly to the purchaser.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The purchaser shall be responsible for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Reading the terms of a land disposition agreement executed for a Fixed Pricing Program disposition; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Signing the land disposition agreement posted online by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Baltimore City Code, Article 13 §§ 2-7 (h), (w)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
