<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-501-2, Part II</num>
  <heading>Commercial Driver License</heading>
  <para name="scope">
    <heading>SCOPE</heading>
    <text>This policy applies to all City employees (Civil Service and non-Civil Service) who will operate Commercial Motor Vehicles (CMV) for and/or owned by the Mayor and City Council of Baltimore. The purpose of this policy is to outline the requirements for all Commercial Driver License (CDL) holders to maintain a City of Baltimore Driver Permit and the specifics of the physical examinations and testing procedures, according to the federal Department of Transportation (DOT) regulations.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="requirements">
    <heading>REQUIREMENTS</heading>
    <text>In order to operate a City-owned Mayor's Motor Vehicle Freeze Committee (MMVFC) or activity-assigned vehicle, an employee must meet all of the requirements of <cite path="§AM-501-2, Part I">AM-501-2, Part I</cite>. Upon meeting all of the requirements, an employee will be issued a City of Baltimore Driver Permit by the Department of Finance, Division of Occupational Safety (DOS).</text>
    <text>In addition, all City drivers operating a CMV for and/or owned by the Mayor and City Council of Baltimore are subject to the provisions of the federal DOT regulations. The regulations require that all CDL holders be randomly tested for alcohol and drugs and successfully complete a physical examination every two (2) years, effective January 1, 1995.</text>
    <text>A City of Baltimore Driver Permit is valid for three (3) years and is renewable, only if the employee completes a Driver Re-certification Training Course and continues to meet all of the requirements of the Motor Vehicle policies in the <em>Administrative Manual </em>Section 501. Drivers are to notify their immediate supervisor of conditions that adversely change their driving status.</text>
    <text>A CMV, according to 49 CFR 382.107, means "a motor vehicle or combination of motor vehicles used in commerce to transport passengers or property if the motor vehicle:</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>has a gross combination weight rating of 26,001 or more pounds inclusive of a towed unit with a gross vehicle weight rating if more than 10,000 rounds; or</li>
        <li>has a gross vehicle weight rating of 26,001 or more pounds; or</li>
        <li>is designated to transport 16 or more passengers, including the driver; or</li>
        <li>is of any size and is used in the transportation of materials found to be hazardous for the purposes of the Hazardous Materials Transportation Act and which require the motor vehicle to be placarded under the hazardous Materials Regulations (49 CFR part 172, subpart F)."</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
  </para>
  <para name="cdl-biennial-physical-examination">
    <heading>CDL BIENNIAL PHYSICAL EXAMINATION</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this examination is to determine a driver's physical qualifications to operate a CMV according to requirements and guidelines in 49 CFR 391.41-49. All City drivers are required to successfully complete this examination and obtain a two-year Medical Examiner's Certificate (i.e.: DOT Card) from the City of Baltimore Occupational Medical Services (Mercy Clinic). The City of Baltimore does not recognize Medical Examiner's Certificates (DOT Cards) obtained from any outside medical facility.</text>
    <text>The CDL biennial physical examination will consist of:</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Reviewing medical history.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
    <text>Checking for the following:</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Limbs (foot, leg, hand and arm) and their corresponding motion and function (including fingers &amp; hands for power grasping);</li>
        <li>Insulin dependent diabetes;</li>
        <li>Cardiovascular disease;</li>
        <li>Respiratory functions;</li>
        <li>High blood pressure;</li>
        <li>Vascular, rheumatic, arthritic, orthopedic, muscular, or neuromuscular disease;</li>
        <li>Epilepsy or any condition likely to cause a loss of consciousness;</li>
        <li>Mental, nervous, organic, or functional disease or psychiatric disorder;</li>
        <li>Vision disorder;</li>
        <li>Hearing function; and also</li>
        <li>Substance use.</li>
        <li>Performing breath alcohol and urine drug tests, according to City policy.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
    <text>Failure to successfully meet any of the requirements of the CDL biennial physical examination will result in disqualification from receiving the Medical Examiner's Certificate (DOT Card) and the driver will be considered as "Does Not Meet Standards (DMS)."</text>
    <text>Depending upon the outcome of the employee's physical examination, the employee may receive a Medical Examiner's Certificate (DOT Card) for either three (3) months, six (6) months or one (1) year in place of the two-year Medical Examiner's Certificate and is considered "Temporarily Qualified (TQ)".</text>
    <text>An employee may also be "Deferred (DEFF)" from receiving a Medical Examiner's Certificate (DOT Card) until additional required information is forwarded to the Mercy Clinic by the employee. It is required that this information be received by the Mercy Clinic within fourteen (14) workdays.</text>
    <text>If an employee is classified as "Temporarily Disqualified (TD)", the employee must recover from the physical condition(s) that lead to the limitation(s) prior to being issued the Medical Examiner's Certificate (DOT Card). Employees are required to closely follow all medical directions for rapid full recovery.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="cdl-drug-testing-procedure">
    <heading>CDL DRUG TESTING PROCEDURE</heading>
    <text>DOS maintains the listing of CDL drivers from which random selections are made for drug and/or alcohol testing. Agencies must supply the names of employees and any subsequent changes with CDL to DOS within 10 workdays.</text>
    <text>DOS may notify the agency of the names of employees requiring CDL biennial physicals prior to the expiration of the two-year Medical Examiner's Certificate (DOT Card). . At that point, the agency human resources/personnel designee must contact the Mercy Clinic to schedule examinations. Agencies will receive a daily list from the Mercy Clinic with the names of CDL holders that need to report for testing on the scheduled day.</text>
    <text>The agency human resources/personnel designee will notify the employee selected to be at the Mercy Clinic, 323 North Calvert Street, at the beginning of the employee's shift. The employee will report to the Mercy Clinic with the following: a completed Request for Services Form (#28- 1608-5151), a completed Supervisory Drug/Alcohol Testing Order form (#28-1608-5157), and City photo identification. <em>(Note: The drug/alcohol testing order form does not have to be signed by a Substance Abuse Control Officer, SACO).</em></text>
  </para>
  <para name="random-tests">
    <heading>RANDOM TESTS</heading>
    <text>All CDL employees shall be subject to regulated drug and alcohol testing as enumerated in the Baltimore City Substance Abuse Control Policy.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="test-results">
    <heading>TEST RESULTS</heading>
    <text>Negative Test Results: DOS will receive a written report stating negative test results. . The employee will continue to work and will be subject to future testing if selected again by the random selection process.</text>
    <text>Positive Test Results: DOS will receive a written report stating positive test results. DOS will suspend the employee's driving privileges.</text>
  </para>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" effective="2012-05-18" display="true">May 18, 2012</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" effective="2018-07-25" display="true">July 25, 2018</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-106-1">AM-106-1</cite> City of Baltimore Safety Program</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-500-1">AM-500-1</cite> Smoke-Free Workplace</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-1">AM-501-1</cite> City-Owned Vehicles</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-2, Part I">AM-501-2, Part I</cite> Training Courses, Drivers Permits, Authorizations, and Licenses for City Owned Vehicles</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-2-1">AM-501-2-1</cite> Obtaining a Driver Permit for City-Owned Vehicles</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-2-2">AM-501-2-2</cite> Notification of City Vehicle Policy</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-6">AM-501-6</cite> Vehicle Maintenance/Repairs</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-8">AM-501-8</cite> Activity-Assigned Vehicles</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-10">AM-501-10</cite> Motor Vehicle Accident</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-11">AM-501-11</cite> Vehicle Damage and Malfunction</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-12">AM-501-12</cite> Use of Communication Devices Prohibited When Operating City Motor Vehicles or Driving Personal Vehicles for City Business</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-14">AM-501-14</cite> Seat Belt Use</annotation>
  </annotations>
</section>
