<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-502-1-1</num>
  <heading>Procedure for Disposal of Records – Sending Records to Archives</heading>
  <text>
    <table>
      <thead>
        <tr>
          <th>RESPONSIBILITY</th>
          <th>ACTION</th>
        </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <th>Agency Head</th>
          <td>
            <p><strong>1.</strong> Review approved Records Retention Schedule. If none exists, contact Records Management Officer to create same.</p>
            <p><strong>2. </strong>Determine need to dispose of records no longer deemed necessary.</p>
            <p><strong>3. </strong>Inform Records Management Officer of records that need to be disposed of.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>Records Management Officer</th>
          <td>
            <p><strong>4.</strong> Inspect records. Review agency retention schedule.</p>
            <p><strong>5.</strong> Determine method of disposal and submit recommendations to Agency Head.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>Agency Head</th>
          <td><strong>6.</strong> Approve findings and return to Records Management Officer.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>Records Management Officer</th>
          <td><strong>7.</strong> Forward same to City Records Committee and return approved form to Agency Head.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>Agency Head</th>
          <td>
            <p><strong>8.</strong> Dispose of records by method determined from Records Management Officer. Coordinate movement of records to Archives and Records Center.</p>
            <p><strong>9. </strong>Pack and label the records in regulation storage boxes. Boxes can be obtained from the City's designated supply vendors (15"x12"x10", with lid). Each box must contain material from one schedule only. Records should be packed in the order they were kept in the office files. All boxes must be correctly labeled. Information concerning the label is to be placed under the handle, and must be legible and complete.</p>
            <p><strong>10. </strong>Complete a copy of a Records Transmittal Request form or memo and forward to Records Management Officer. This form must be approved by the Archives staff before the records are sent. Box descriptions should be general; e.g.</p>
            <p>Correspondence, A-D</p>
            <p>Contracts, 10071-12007</p>
            <p>Case Files, M. Brown-A. Jones</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>Records Management Officer</th>
          <td><strong>11. </strong>Approve Records Transmittal Request form and call Agency Head.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>Agency Head</th>
          <td><strong>12. </strong>Coordinate transport of records at a time approved by the Archives staff. Assistance in loading and stacking on shelves may also be required.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>Records Management Officer</th>
          <td><strong>13. </strong>This memo will be referenced when requesting records from the Records Management Center.</td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </text>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" effective="1988-12-15" display="true">December 15, 1988</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" effective="2004-08-08" display="true">August 8, 2004</annotation>
  </annotations>
</section>
