<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-501-2, Part 1</num>
  <heading>Training Courses, Driver Permits, Authorizations and Licenses for City-Owned Vehicles</heading>
  <para name="scope">
    <heading>SCOPE</heading>
    <text>Except as otherwise stated, this Policy applies to all City employees (civil and non-civil service) who will operate a vehicle for and/or owned by the Mayor and City Council of Baltimore. This policy does not apply to employees of the Baltimore City Sherriff's Office, or the Baltimore Police Department, who have received State certification for operating an emergency vehicle. Eligibility for a City of Baltimore Driver Permit/Authorization (CBDP/A) is contingent upon a City employee having a valid Maryland State driver's license with the appropriate license class code, (employees with licenses from another State not Maryland may be eligible if that State is proven to be their actual state of residency…i.e. commute between the state and City employment each day and evening of employee's work day/shift), and meeting the requirements for such Permit/Authorization as outlined in this policy. A City employee who does not have a valid City of Baltimore Driver Permit will not be allowed to operate any type of City-owned vehicle. A CBDP/A may be suspended or revoked by the Department of Finance, Division of Occupational Safety (DOS), or the employee's agency head when circumstances warrant it.</text>
    <text>Failure to maintain (for any reason) a CBDP/A, may result in the immediate transfer, demotion, and/or termination of the affected employee. A current file of individuals who's CBDP/As and/or State drivers' licenses have been suspended or revoked shall be maintained by DOS and at the agency level. Employees who have been approved for a CBDP/A, but reside in another state outside of Maryland must provide DOS with a certified copy of their State Driving Record every six (6) months, in January and July.</text>
    <text>Issuance and/or reinstatement of a CBDP/A, upon request of a City Agency <u>shall</u> be solely the discretion of DOS.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="training">
    <heading>TRAINING</heading>
    <text>
      <u>Basic Driver Training</u>
    </text>
    <text>The Basic Driver Training Course provides instruction in basic driving and safety techniques for the Mayor's Motor Vehicle Freeze Committee (MMVFC) and activity-assigned vehicles. DOS and/or their assigned representatives administer this course. DOS designs the course (which currently includes the National Safety Council's Defensive Driving Course, vision examination, and other required elements. Although these may change in the future, all aspects of the course must be passed in order to attain or retain a City Driver's Permit. A MMVFC/activity-assigned vehicle is defined as a car, station wagon, or truck with a 2,000 pound load capacity or less. (See <cite path="§AM-501-2, Part II">AM-501-2, Part II</cite>, <em>Commercial Driver License</em> (CDL) policy. Completing this course in full is a prerequisite for obtaining a CBDP/A.</text>
    <text>
      <u>Blanket Exception for the Baltimore City Fire Department</u>
    </text>
    <text>Upon meeting all of the aforementioned requirements, an employee of the Baltimore City Fire department must be at least 19 years of age with at least eighteen (18) months of licensed driving experience.</text>
    <text>
      <u>Recertification Driver Training</u>
    </text>
    <text>The Recertification Driver Training Course provides an update to the preceding Basic Driver Training Course in driving and safety techniques for the MMVFC and activity-assigned vehicles. DOS and/or their assigned representatives administer this course. This course is designed as an update to the Basis Driver Training Course and must be completed in full every three years to maintain an active and current CBDP/A.</text>
    <text>
      <u>Requirement for Renewals of Basic and Recertification Training</u>
    </text>
    <text>If an employee fails to renew his CBDP/A by participating/complying with the above referenced required training classes, the employee may be subject to the appropriate action which may include suspension of driving privileges by DOS and/or disciplinary action by agency for insubordination (up to and including termination). Please note that if it has been five (5) or more years since an employee has participated/complied with his/her Recertification Driving Training Course, the employee will be required to attend the Basic Driving Training Course again instead of the Recertification Course in order to receive CBDP/A.</text>
    <text>
      <u>Special Purpose Vehicle Training</u>
    </text>
    <text>The Special Purpose Vehicle Training Course is administered by each agency having personnel who are required to use special purpose vehicles. A special purpose vehicle is defined as any vehicle that requires anything other than a Class C license to operate. Prior to special purpose vehicle training, the agency must have an approved training course on file with DOS and special purpose instructors shall maintain and timely keep up to date any and all required and/or suggested credentials authorizing he/she to instruct.</text>
    <text>An agency head must notify DOS by memo within five (5) days after employees have completed the course. The memo should state those employees who have been qualified to operate a special purpose vehicle and the type of vehicle each is permitted to operate. DOS will issue the Special Purpose Vehicle Permit to each qualified employee.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="requirements-for-obtaining-a-driver-permit">
    <heading>REQUIREMENTS FOR OBTAINING A DRIVER PERMIT</heading>
    <text>
      <u>Basic Vehicle Permit</u>
    </text>
    <text>Upon request of a City Agency for an employee to operate a City-owned MMVFC or activity-assigned vehicle, an employee must meet all of the below listed requirements. Upon meeting all of the requirements, an individual (must be a City employee not a contractual employee or volunteer) will be issued a City of Baltimore Driver Permit by DOS. A City of Baltimore Driver Permit is valid for three (3) years and is renewable only if the employee completes the Driver Recertification Training Course (every three (3) years) and continues to meet <u>all</u> of the following listed requirements.</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Be at least 21 years of age with at least three (3) years of licensed driving experience.</li>
        <li>Possess a current and valid Maryland State driver's license (employees with licenses from another State outside of Maryland may be eligible if that State is proven to be their actual state of residency … i.e., commute between the state and City employment each day and evening of employee's work day/shift), with the appropriate license class code.</li>
        <li>Have successfully completed the Basic Driver Training Course.</li>
        <li>Have reviewed and signed a NOTIFICATION OF CITY VEHICLE POLICY (<cite path="§AM-501-2-2">AM-501-2-2</cite>) provided by DOS.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
    <text>As noted above, employees that have allowed his/her CBDP/A to lapse/expire for five (5) or more years, shall be required to take the BASIC course again in lieu of taking a Recertification course in order to regain their COB driving privileges.</text>
    <text>
      <u>Special Purpose Vehicle Authorization</u>
    </text>
    <text>In order to operate any type of City-owned special purpose vehicle an employee must meet all of the below listed requirements. Upon meeting all of the requirements, a Special Vehicle Permit will be issued by DOS indicating the type of special purpose vehicle he/she is authorized to operate. This authorization is valid for three (3) years and is renewable only if the employee successfully completes an additional Special Vehicle Training Course and continues to meet <u>all</u> of the following requirements.</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Be at least 21 years of age.</li>
        <li>Possess a valid State driver's license with the appropriate license class code.</li>
        <li>Possess a current and valid City of Baltimore Driver Permit.</li>
        <li>Have successfully completed a Special Vehicle Training Course.</li>
        <li>Have reviewed and signed a NOTIFICATION OF CITY VEHICLE POLICY provided by DOS.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
    <text>
      <u>Exception to Age Requirement</u>
    </text>
    <text>If an agency head finds it necessary for an employee under age 21 and/or with less than three (3) years of licensed driving experience to operate a City-owned vehicle on a basic or special vehicle permit, a memo detailing the reason(s) for the request should be forwarded to DOS. A certified copy of the employee's Motor Vehicle Administration driving record must be attached to the memo for evaluation. DOS will notify the agency head of the decision on a case-by-case basis. Any blanket exceptions need approval by the Board of Estimates.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="suspension-or-revocation-of-city-of-baltimore-driver-permit/-authorization">
    <heading>SUSPENSION OR REVOCATION OF CITY OF BALTIMORE DRIVER PERMIT/ AUTHORIZATION</heading>
    <text>Suspension or revocation of an employee's City of Baltimore Driver Permit/Authorization by the employee's agency head must be reported by memo within three (3) workdays to the MMVFC and to DOS. The memo must cite the reason(s) for the suspension or revocation and specify actions taken to prevent recurrences. DOS may revoke or suspend an employee's CBDP/A even if the employee's agency head elects not to take such action. Further, an agency may request DOS to suspend or revoke an employee's CBDP/A when warranted and agency shall provide documentation and/or communication memorializing that the request is warranted. This documentation shall be noted in the employee's electronic driver's file as well as in his/her hard file, both of which is maintained/housed at DOS.</text>
    <text>An employee's City of Baltimore Driver Permit/Authorization may be suspended or revoked for any of the following reasons, which include but are not limited to:</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Driving any vehicle (City owned or privately owned) while under the influence of alcohol or drugs.</li>
        <li>Any violation to the Maryland State Driver's Handbook or restriction placed on a State driver's license (including but not limited to refusing a chemical test, interlock device restriction, even when employer vehicle exempted, if an alcohol related restriction code is on and/or added to our state license, etc…)</li>
        <li>Leaving the scene of an accident or failure to report an accident in accordance with <cite path="§AM-501-10">AM-501-10</cite>.</li>
        <li>Operating or ordering the operation of City-owned vehicle with the knowledge that the vehicle has safety deficiencies.</li>
        <li>Unsafe driving practices or persistent violation of safety rules. Negligence, misuse, and/or abuse of City-owned vehicle.</li>
        <li>Frequent accidents, i.e. more than two (2) accidents in a year.</li>
        <li>Failure to properly secure a City-owned vehicle, i.e. runaway vehicle.</li>
        <li>Suspension, revocation, or expiration of State driver's license.</li>
        <li>Failure to inform supervisor and DOS of the suspension, revocation, or expiration of State driver's license.</li>
        <li>Failure to pay traffic or parking fines for violations incurred while using a City-owned vehicle.</li>
        <li>Any points on State driving record.</li>
        <li>Failure to perform vehicle safety and operating checks.</li>
        <li>Using a City-owned vehicle (or privately owned vehicle while on duty for the City) for pleasure, to conduct personal business, and/or to transport passengers not engaged in official City business.</li>
        <li>Medical problems which may interfere with the safe operation of a City-owned vehicle, as determined by the City of Baltimore Occupational Medical Services (Mercy Clinic).</li>
        <li>Failure to inform supervisor and DOS of the medical problems which may interfere with the safe operation of a City-owned vehicle.</li>
        <li>Alteration/forgery of a CBDP/A by employee.</li>
        <li>Obtaining fuel while City driver permit is suspended.</li>
        <li>Use of personal communication devices (hand-held or hands-free) in accordance with <cite path="§AM-501-12">AM-501-12</cite>.</li>
        <li>Smoking in a City-owned vehicle in accordance with <cite path="§AM-500-01">AM-500-01</cite>.</li>
        <li>Failure to wear seat belts by anyone in the vehicle in accordance with <cite path="§AM-501-14">AM-501-14</cite></li>
        <li>Expiration and/or lapsing of CBDP/A permit and/or any other licenses required to fulfill employee's job responsibilities;</li>
        <li>Failure to comply/show-up at scheduled medical appointments at City clinic that are scheduled by agency, DOS and/or any other agency in order to maintain relevant licenses to fulfill job responsibilities;</li>
        <li>Failure to comply/show up for random drug and/or alcohol random testing;</li>
        <li>By request of authorized personnel of employee's City agency, and/or other authorized City personnel and/or authorized personnel and when warranted and documentation has been forwarded to DOS identifying why the suspension/revocation is warranted;</li>
        <li>Per recommendation and/or request by a professional within the City of Baltimore Employee Assistance Program;</li>
        <li>For out of State licensed approved drivers/employees of the City of Baltimore, if an updated Motor Vehicle Report is not provided to DOS every 6 months;</li>
        <li>Other reasons or circumstances which are deemed as unsafe operation of a City-owned vehicle by DOS or the department head.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
    <text>The Law and Police Departments are also responsible for reporting any of the above instances within three (3) workdays to DOS.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="reporting-suspension,-revocation-or-expiration-of-state-driver's-license">
    <heading>REPORTING SUSPENSION, REVOCATION OR EXPIRATION OF STATE DRIVER'S LICENSE</heading>
    <text>An employee must officially notify, either in person or in writing, his supervisor and DOS of the suspension, revocation, or expiration of his/her State driver's license within one (1) workday.  Failure to notify as required may result in suspension of the employee from work.</text>
    <text>DOS and the agency head will periodically obtain and review the Maryland State driving record of each employee who possesses a City of Baltimore Driver Permit in order to monitor compliance with the <em>Administrative Manual</em> policy. Employers who have been approved for a CBDP/A but reside in another State outside of Maryland must provide DOS with a certified copy of their State Driving Record every six (6) months, in January and July. Appropriate action will be initiated as required for employees who are in violation of this policy. The appropriate action may include suspension of driving privileges by DOS and/or disciplinary action by agency for insubordination (up to and including termination).</text>
  </para>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" effective="2018-07-25" display="true">July 25, 2018</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" effective="2019-06-26" display="true">June 26, 2019</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-106-1">AM-106-1</cite> City of Baltimore Safety Program</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-500-1">AM-500-1</cite> SmOKE-FREE WORKPLACE</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-1">AM-501-1</cite> City-Owned Vehicles</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-2, Part II">AM-501-2, Part II</cite> Commercial Driver License (CDL)</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-2-1">AM-501-2-1</cite> Obtaining a Driver Permit for City-Owned Vehicles</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-2-2">AM-501-2-2</cite> Notification of City Vehicle Policy</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-6">AM-501-6</cite> Vehicle Maintenance/Repairs</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-8">AM-501-8</cite> Activity-Assigned Vehicles</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-10">AM-501-10</cite> Motor Vehicle Accident</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-11">AM-501-11</cite> Vehicle Damage and Malfunction</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-12">AM-501-12</cite> Use of Communications Devices Prohibited when operating a City owned Motor Vehicle or driving a personal vehicle on City business</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies"><cite path="§AM-501-14">AM-501-14</cite> Safety Belt</annotation>
  </annotations>
</section>
