<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>GENERAL PROVISIONS</heading>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">
      <cite doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Code" path="|28|§8-5">Baltimore City Code Article 28, § 8-5</cite>
    </annotation>
    <annotation type="Editor's Notes" dest="container">The attached regulations have been submitted to the Director of the Department of Legislative Reference for COBRA codification in accordance with <cite doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Code" path="|general|4|4|4-401">§ 4-401, Title 4 { Administrative Procedure Act – Regulations }</cite> of the <cite doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Code" path="|general">General Provisions Article of the Baltimore City Code</cite>. The attached regulations have not been reviewed by the Department of Legislative Reference for adherence to COBRA formatting and are subject to non-substantive formatting changes.</annotation>
  </annotations>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Adoption, Applicability, and Scope of Regulations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Adoption.</text>
      <text>The Baltimore City Department of Finance ("DOF") adopts these rules and regulations under <cite doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Code" path="|28">City Code Article 28</cite>, §8-5.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Applicability.</text>
      <text>These rules and regulations are in addition to all applicable laws found in the <cite doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Code" path="|28">City Code Article 28</cite>, other applicable sections of the City Code, and the Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Scope of Regulations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Effective July 1, 2021, certain homeowners are eligible to apply during a two-month period beginning February 15 of that fiscal year to have their properties withheld from the annual tax sale list.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text><cite path="05.18.01.01">This section</cite> applies to the sale of a dwelling with an assessed value of $250,000 or less.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The aggregate tax and lien liability of all properties withheld from the annual tax sale list may not exceed $2 million in any tax year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In <cite path="05.18.01">this chapter</cite>, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Dwelling" has the meaning stated in State Tax-Property-Article § 9-105(a)(5).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Finance" means the Baltimore City Department of Finance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"HCD" means the Baltimore Department of Housing and Community Development.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Homeowner" has the meaning stated in State Tax-Property-Article §9-105(a)(7).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Program" means the Tax Sale Exemption Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Tax" has the meaning stated in State Tax-Property-Article § 14-801(d).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Withheld"</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>means that dwellings will be removed from the list of properties eligible for tax sale, but</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>does not mean that the outstanding tax and lien liabilities for the dwelling have been abated.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Eligibility Criteria.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Homeowners are eligible for participation in the Tax Sale Exemption Program if</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>they meet certain criteria and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>there are available funds to cover the tax and lien liability for the dwelling.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A homeowner is eligible for participation in the Tax Sale Exemption Program if</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>the homeowner has resided in the dwelling for at least 15 years; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>has either</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>a total annual household income of less than $36,000;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>is at least 65 years old and has annual earned income of $75,000 or less; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>is an adult who is</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>currently receiving disability benefits from the Federal Social Security Disability Insurance program or the Supplemental Security Income program, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>has annual earned income of $75,000 or less.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Determination of eligibility.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The determination of whether a homeowner meets the eligibility requirements outlined in <cite path="05.18.01.03">this section</cite> is based on</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>the application documentation provided, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>a database verification process.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The tax and lien liability for the homeowner's dwelling shall not cause the aggregate tax and lien liability of all withheld dwellings to exceed $2 million.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Terms of exemption.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A homeowner shall apply on an annual basis to have their dwelling withheld from tax sale.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Participation in the program does not signify approval for future years.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Participation in the program does not result in the abatement of any outstanding tax and lien liability of exempted dwellings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Program participants are responsible for making payments on any outstanding tax and lien liability.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Application Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Application deadlines.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Application deadlines will be set annually and advertised on the Finance and HCD    websites.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Application deadlines are</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>binding upon all applicants, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>shall not be altered for an individual applicant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Failure to meet a deadline shall result in the application being rejected.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>By submitting an exemption application</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>an applicant acknowledges these requirements, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>agrees to be bound by the deadlines.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Application submission.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Applications shall be submitted to the Baltimore City Department of Housing and Community Development ("HCD") either:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>electronically at <strong>https://portal.neighborlysoftware.com/baltimoremd/participant</strong>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>by mail to Baltimore City Department of Housing and Community Development, Tax Sale Exemption Program, 417 E Fayette Street, 11<sup>th</sup> Floor, Baltimore, MD 21201;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>in person at 417 E Fayette Street, 11<sup>th</sup> floor; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>by email to dhcd.taxsaleinfo@baltimorecity.gov, subject line: Tax Sale Exemption Application.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The City of Baltimore is not</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>responsible for any connectivity or application submission issues experienced by the applicant, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>will not grant an extension of any deadline due to issues beyond the control of the Department of Housing and Community Development.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Complete applications shall include copies of the following documentation:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>a copy of a photo ID for the applicant issued by</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>the United States government;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>the State of Maryland; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>the City of Baltimore;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>any two of the following documents showing the current address of the applicant:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>utility bills;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>photo ID issued by the United States government, State of Maryland, or City of Baltimore; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Social Security (SSA, SSDI, SSI) award letters.; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>a complete Income Information form which includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>the total number of people in the household;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>number of adults, school-aged and non-school-aged children;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>total gross household income; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>proof of household income.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Proof of household income may include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>two pay stubs from current employer, within last two months of employment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Social Security (SSA, SSDI, SSI) award letters;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>pension statements;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Unemployment or Workers' Compensation statements or award letters; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>other documentation that confirms the income provided in the Income Information form.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The online and paper form of the application shall list documents accepted to validate eligibility for this program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Tax Sale Ombudsman shall provide information and answer applicant questions about</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>the application process, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>required supporting documentation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Application review.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Hard copy applications received by mail or personal delivery shall be date and time stamped upon receipt by the Department of Housing and Community Development.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Date and time stamped hard copy applications shall be entered in the Neighborly project management database by HCD personnel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Applications received by HCD shall be reviewed for completeness and eligibility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Applications shall be deemed complete if the application includes all required documentation and all required application fields are completed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Applications shall be deemed eligible if</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>all eligibility criteria are met, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>all required documentation has been verified.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Department of Finance shall be notified of applications deemed eligible upon review.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Incomplete applications.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Applications shall be deemed incomplete when the homeowner</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>does not fully complete the application,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>does not provide required documentation, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>completed fields in the application are not legible.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For incomplete applications, HCD shall contact the applicant</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>using the contact information provided on the application</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>to request additional information or clarification.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Eligibility review.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Applications shall be deemed ineligible if the homeowner does not meet the eligibility criteria based on</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>documentation provided, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>the application and documentation verification process.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department of Housing and Community Development shall notify the applicant using the contact information provided on the application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Fund availability.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For all eligible applications, the Department of Finance shall assess</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>the amount of tax and lien liability on the applicant dwelling, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>the aggregate tax and lien liability for the Program at the time of receiving the application.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the amount of tax and lien liability on the applicant dwelling causes the aggregate tax and lien liability of the Program to exceed $2 million, the Department of Finance shall</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>reject the application, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>assess successive applications until it identifies an application with outstanding tax and lien liability that will not exceed the Program's aggregate tax and lien liability limit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When the remaining Program funding available is below $750</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>the application process shall be closed and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>no additional applications shall be approved.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Department of Finance shall notify HCD of approved applications based on fund availability.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Department of Housing and Community Development shall notify the applicant using the contact information provided on the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Department of Finance shall deny an application if</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>the property is not on the tax sale list, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>if the lien amount is greater than the remaining available funds.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If the Department of Finance denies an application,</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>it shall notify HCD as to why the application was denied, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>the Department of Housing and Community Development shall notify the applicant using the contact information provided on the application.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Fraudulent Applications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If an applicant is found to have provided false information the application shall be deemed to be fraudulent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If an application is deemed fraudulent and the tax sale has not yet occurred</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>the exemption shall be revoked and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>the property shall be placed back onto the tax sale list.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If an application is deemed fraudulent and the tax sale has occurred the City shall pursue available legal action.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Notice.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department of Housing and Community Development and the Department of Finance shall issue notice to the public about this Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Schedule of notice.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department of Finance's Bureau of Revenue Collection shall issue a notice as part of the Mayor's Message in the July 1 property tax bills.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The City's Tax Sale Ombudsman shall issue a notice to dwellings that are owneroccupied, have an assessed value of $250,000 or less, and have delinquent property tax accounts in January.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Department of Finance's Bureau of Revenue Collection shall issue a notice to dwellings receiving a Final Bill and Legal Notice in February.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
</container>
