<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-103-2</num>
  <heading>Flags at Half-Staff</heading>
  <para name="scope">
    <heading>SCOPE</heading>
    <text>This policy provides necessary direction regarding the flying of flags at half-staff in all or designated City buildings. By Presidential Proclamation, the flying of the United States Flag shall be flown at half-staff in those City buildings where the flag is displayed. The Governor of the State of Maryland is the responsible official who determines when the State of Maryland Flag shall be flown at Half-staff in those City buildings where the flag is displayed. The Mayor of Baltimore City is the responsible official who determines when it is appropriate for the City of Baltimore to recognize a solemn occasion by directing the flying of the City of Baltimore Flag at half-staff in all or designated City buildings.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="solemn-occasion-–-city-flag">
    <heading>SOLEMN OCCASION – CITY FLAG</heading>
    <text>When it is appropriate for the City of Baltimore to recognize a solemn occasion, the mayor shall direct that the City8 Flag be flown at half-staff in all City buildings. It may be appropriate for the Mayor to direct that the City Flag be flown at half-staff for a specified period in designated City buildings. The Mayor's directive shall be forwarded to the Head, Bureau of General Services, 8<sup>th</sup> Floor, Wolman Municipal Office Building, for subsequent instruction to the employees.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="solemn-occasion-–-state-flag">
    <heading>SOLEMN OCCASION – STATE FLAG</heading>
    <text>The Governor of the State of Maryland is the responsible official who determines when the State of Maryland Flag shall be flown at half-staff in those buildings displaying the State Flag. The Department of General Services, after notification from the Governor's office, shall notify all necessary offices relative to the proper display of the State Flag.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="solemn-occasion-–-united-states-flag">
    <heading>SOLEMN OCCASION – UNITED STATES FLAG</heading>
    <text>The United States Flag shall fly at half-staff for 30 days from the day of death of a President or former President; for 10 days from the death of for a Vice President, Chief Justice or retired Chief Justice of the United States, or Speaker of the House of Representatives; from day of death until burial of an Associate Justice of the Supreme Court, cabinet member, former Vice President, or Senate President Pro Tempore, Majority or Minority Senate Leader, or Majority or Minority House Leader; for a United States Senator, Representative, Territorial Delegate, or the Resident Commissioner of Puerto Rico on the day of death and the following day within the Metropolitan area of the District of Columbia and from day of death until burial within the decedent's State congressional district, territory, or commonwealth; and for the death of the governor of the state, territory, or possession of the United States from day of death until burial within that state, territory or possession.</text>
  </para>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" effective="1989-11-01" display="true">November 1, 1989</annotation>
  </annotations>
</section>
