<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-114-1</num>
  <heading>City Signs</heading>
  <para name="scope">
    <heading>SCOPE</heading>
    <text>This policy applies to all City signs and banners placed on or over the City right-of-way which are for the purpose of informing the public.  Examples of such signs and banners are:</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Directional signs;</li>
        <li>Community signs;</li>
        <li>Street banners announcing events; and</li>
        <li>Building identification signs.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
    <text>Excluded from the scope of this policy are street identification signs, traffic control signs, e.g., No Parking, No Stopping, Left Turn Only, etc., and legally permitted commercial signs.</text>
    <text>Signs covered by this policy must be approved by the City's Signing Committee prior to the formation of any contractual agreements, fabrication of signs, or installation, removal, or repair of signs.    The Bureau of the Budget and Management Research must certify all SIGN AUTHORIZATION REQUESTS   (28-1458-5129) for availability of funds.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="categories-of-signs">
    <heading>CATEGORIES OF SIGNS</heading>
    <text>There are two categories of signs.</text>
    <text>PERMANENT - - a sign which does not have an anticipated date of removal.</text>
    <text>TEMPORARY - - a sign which has an anticipated date of removal.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="responsibilities">
    <heading>RESPONSIBILITIES</heading>
    <text>
      <u>Signing Committee</u>
    </text>
    <text>The Signing Committee is appointed by the Mayor and is responsible for:</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Contacting the appropriate City agencies, boards, and commissions to obtain sign approvals as required by <cite doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Charter">the City Charter</cite>, City Code, ordinances or other legal authority.</li>
        <li>Evaluating SIGN AUTHORIZATION REQUESTS  (28-1258-5068) based on the following criteria:</li>
        <li>Durability;</li>
        <li>Public safety;</li>
        <li>Necessity; and</li>
        <li>Quality of design.</li>
        <li>Processing all SIGN AUTHORIZATION REQUESTS in accordance with this policy, to include approving or disapproving such requests.</li>
        <li>Ordering the repair or removal of signs which are:</li>
        <li>Duplicated or made obsolete by other signs or sign systems;</li>
        <li>Deteriorated in appearance or structure; and</li>
        <li>Detrimental to the public health or welfare.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
  </para>
  <para name="transportation">
    <heading>TRANSPORTATION</heading>
    <text>The Department of Transportation is responsible for evaluating all SIGN AUTHORIZATION REQUESTS. In addition, the Department:</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Determines the best location for the requested sign;</li>
        <li>Obtains clearance and approvals from utility and City agencies</li>
        <li>Processes all SIGN  AUTHORIZATION  REQUESTS  in accordance with this policy to include approving or disapproving such requests;</li>
        <li>Coordinates sign repair requests reported by telephone and directly to the Department.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
  </para>
  <para name="signs:-installation,-removal-or-repair">
    <heading>SIGNS: INSTALLATION, REMOVAL OR REPAIR</heading>
    <text>To request installation, removal  or  repair  of  a  sign, a SIGN AUTHORIZATION REQUEST must be prepared and submitted to the Signing  Committee,  Attn:    Commissioner of Transportation,   5<sup>th</sup> floor, 417  E  Fayette  Street.  Signs  which  need  repair  should  be reported  to  the  Department  of  Transportation  by  telephone. The Department  of  Transportation  will  then  prepare  the  required  SIGN AUTHORIZATION  REQUEST. SIGN AUTHORIZATION REQUESTS must be submitted  at  least  2  MONTHS  prior  to  the  date  that  action  is required.</text>
  </para>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" effective="1989-07-20" display="true">July 20, 1989</annotation>
  </annotations>
</section>
