<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-101-1</num>
  <heading>Request for Board of Estimates Approval</heading>
  <para name="scope">
    <heading>SCOPE</heading>
    <text>This policy concerns all communications, documents, personnel matters and related actions which must be considered and approved by the Board of Estimates.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="documents-or-communications">
    <heading>DOCUMENTS OR COMMUNICATIONS</heading>
    <text>Documents or communications which require Board of Estimates' approval, but which are not concerned with personnel matters, must be submitted to the Board in the following manner:</text>
    <text>• Original and 5 copies --Address and forward to:</text>
    <text>
      <em>President and Honorable Members</em>
    </text>
    <text>
      <em>Board of Estimates</em>
    </text>
    <text>
      <em>204 City Hall</em>
    </text>
    <text>• 1 copy -- Forward to:</text>
    <text>
      <em>Chief of Staff</em>
    </text>
    <text>
      <em>Office of the Mayor</em>
    </text>
    <text>
      <em>250 City Hall</em>
    </text>
  </para>
  <para name="personnel-matters">
    <heading>PERSONNEL MATTERS</heading>
    <text>All personnel matters which require Board of Estimates' approval must be submitted to the Board in the following manner:</text>
    <text>• Original and 5 copies -- Address to:</text>
    <text>
      <em>President and Honorable Members</em>
    </text>
    <text>
      <em>Board of Estimates</em>
    </text>
    <text>
      <em>204 City Hall</em>
    </text>
    <text>Forward directly to:</text>
    <text>
      <em>Secretary</em>
    </text>
    <text>
      <em>Expenditure Control Committee</em>
    </text>
    <text>
      <em>469 City Hall</em>
    </text>
    <text>• 1 copy -- Forward a copy of the cover MEMO concerning the request to:</text>
    <text>
      <em>Chief of Staff</em>
    </text>
    <text>
      <em>Office of the Mayor</em>
    </text>
    <text>
      <em>250 City Hall</em>
    </text>
  </para>
  <para name="request-for-board-of-estimates'-approval">
    <heading>REQUEST FOR BOARD OF ESTIMATES' APPROVAL</heading>
    <text>All requests for approval by the Board of Estimates must be submitted on City memo paper and be formatted as in <a href="./AM-101-1-1.pdf">AM-101-1-1</a> except for Expenditure Authorization Request forms, Travel Request forms, and the Bureau of Purchases' list of informal awards.</text>
    <text>The following are the areas to be discussed in the memo:</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Action Requested by Board of Estimates;</li>
        <li>Amount of Money and Source of Funds;</li>
        <li>Background/Explanation; and</li>
        <li>MBE/WBE Participation - if applicable.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
  </para>
  <para name="prior-approval">
    <heading>PRIOR APPROVAL</heading>
    <text>Prior to submission to the Board of Estimates, the agency must receive approval from the Bureau of the Budget and Management Research (BBMR) regarding all matters that involve expenditure of funds.</text>
    <text>All third party contracts and/or legal documents which bind the City must be reviewed by the Department of Law for form and legal sufficiency. Agency heads must receive approval from the Department of Law prior to submission to BBMR for funding approval.</text>
    <text>The Department of Audits reviews grant awards to the City, subgrantee awards made by City agencies, consultant contracts, change orders, on-call contracts and medical payments. After review and approval by the Department of Audits, the request is placed on the Board of Estimates' agenda. Other areas may be reviewed at the discretion of the auditors or upon request by the Board of Estimates.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="late-approval">
    <heading>LATE APPROVAL</heading>
    <text>Submissions to the Board of Estimates should be made in a timely manner, i.e. prior to the execution of or effective date of the requested action. In those cases where it is not possible to obtain prior approval, a full explanation of the reason must be included in the letter or other request to the Board of Estimates with a copy forwarded to the Mayor's Office, attention of the Chief of Staff.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="approval/disapproval">
    <heading>APPROVAL/DISAPPROVAL</heading>
    <text>Agencies may not act upon their request to the Board of Estimates until the approved copy is received back from the Office of Comptroller's Office, normally within five (5) work days of the Board meeting. If the request has been disapproved, it is returned to the agency indicating disapproval.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="preparation-of-the-board-of-estimates-agenda">
    <heading>PREPARATION OF THE BOARD OF ESTIMATES AGENDA</heading>
    <text>The Office of the Comptroller prepares the agenda for the Board of Estimates. The Comptroller's office issues regulations regarding the deadline for submissions for the agenda, the manner in which items must be submitted, and the dates of Board meetings.</text>
    <text>The general rules are:</text>
    <para>
      <num>1.</num>
      <text>The Board of Estimates meets every Wednesday at 9:00 a.m. in City Hall, Room 215, unless otherwise modified.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>2.</num>
      <text>The deadline for submissions of items is Thursday by 11:00 a.m. for meetings on the following Wednesday, unless notified otherwise.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>3.</num>
      <text>The <u>original</u> request (and required copies) to the Board and/or related document must be submitted in order for an item to be placed on the agenda. A fax, photocopy or incomplete document will not be accepted for the agenda.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>4.</num>
      <text>Prior to the submission of an item for the agenda, the requesting agency is responsible for confirming dates, amounts, and securing the required approvals.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>5.</num>
      <text>A request to withdraw an item must be received no later than 2:00 p.m. on the Friday preceding the Board meeting that is scheduled for the following Wednesday.</text>
    </para>
  </para>
  <para name="&quot;walk-ons&quot;">
    <heading>"WALK-ONS"</heading>
    <text>Items added to the published agenda of the Board of Estimates ("walk-ons") should be limited to emergencies where life or property is in jeopardy, confidential settlements of civil lawsuits, matters requiring immediate action to preclude loss of Federal or State funding, items requiring immediate subsequent approval of the Maryland Board of Public Works and matters of a similar nature. "Walk-ons" should not include routine items which are not on the agenda due to delays in the agency's administrative review and approval process. All requested "walk-ons" for the Administration must be submitted first to the Mayor's Office for review.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="certified-emergency">
    <heading>CERTIFIED EMERGENCY</heading>
    <text>In the event of an emergency of such a nature that the public welfare would be adversely affected by awaiting the approval of the Board of Estimates, the Director of Finance, upon request by the head of the municipal agency involved, may proceed to obtain the supplies, materials, equipment, services or public works required without reference to the procurement procedures outlined in <cite doc="City of Baltimore, Md., Charter">the City Charter</cite>. A full report of any such action shall be promptly submitted to the Board of Estimates.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="related-stationery">
    <heading>RELATED STATIONERY</heading>
    <text>Agencies should not use letterhead when corresponding with the Board of Estimates. The official City MEMORANDUM (26-1418-5007) must be used.</text>
  </para>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Supporting Documents" name="AM-101-1-1">
      <a href="./AM-101-1-1.pdf">AM-101-1-1</a>
    </annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies">AM-230-1 PERSONNEL REQUEST</annotation>
    <annotation type="Related Policies">AM-508-1 LETTERHEAD</annotation>
    <annotation type="history" effective="1989-02-14" display="true">February 14, 1989</annotation>
    <annotation type="history" effective="1998-03-04" display="true">March 4, 1998</annotation>
  </annotations>
</section>
