<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-117-1</num>
  <heading>Security Services: City Owned/Operated Facilities</heading>
  <para name="scope">
    <heading>SCOPE</heading>
    <text>This policy concerns obtaining security services for use in City-Owned/Operated Facilities. The options available to agencies desiring security services consist of the following types of security personnel:</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>City Protection Officers, i.e., off-duty City Police Officers.</li>
        <li>Private security guards.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
  </para>
  <para name="requesting-security-services">
    <heading>REQUESTING SECURITY SERVICES</heading>
    <text>An agency head must request security services by completing a REQUEST FOR SECURITY SERVICES. This form is available from:</text>
    <text>Facilities Security Administrator (410-396-2141)<br/>c/o City Owned Facilities/Overtime and Special Events Unit Baltimore City Police Headquarters<br/>601 E. Fayette Street</text>
    <text>Within 10 work days after receipt, the agency head must return the form to the Facilities Security Administrator for development of a security requirement report. This report will be attached to the form and forwarded to the Prequalification Standards Committee (PSC) for action.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="approval">
    <heading>APPROVAL</heading>
    <text>Upon approval of security services by the PSC, the requesting agency will be notified indicating whether services will be provided by City Protection Officers, private security guards, or by a combination thereof.</text>
    <text>When security services are to be provided through the use of City Protection Officers, the Facilities Security Administrator will implement the security plan. When services are to be provided by private security guards, the agency must send a PURCHASE REQUISITION (28- J 448-5125), approved by the agency's budget analyst, to the Facilities Security Administrator who will forward the approved REQUEST FOR SECURITY SERVICES form with the PURCHASE REQUISITION to the Bureau of Purchases.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="rates">
    <heading>RATES</heading>
    <text>Rates charged for security services will vary depending upon the type of security personnel approved by the PSC. The average overtime rate for Po1ice Officers is $32 an hour; however, the actual rate will vary depending on the individual officer detailed. The rate for private security guards will range from $15 to $25 an hour. Agencies may obtain current rates by</text>
    <text>contacting the Administrator.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="payment">
    <heading>PAYMENT</heading>
    <text>When City Protection Officers are to be utilized, agencies will be charged by a JOURNAL ENTRY (28-1428-5020).</text>
    <text>When private security guards are to be utilized, agencies must submit a DEPARTMENTAL RECEIVING NOTICE FOR PARTIAL SHIPMENT (28-1428-5019), matched with the Purchase Order, to Accounts Payable, Bureau of Accounting and Payroll Services, 401 E. Fayette St.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="compliance">
    <heading>COMPLIANCE</heading>
    <text>All requests for security and the use of such services must comply with the provisions of this policy. Failure to comply with this policy may result in adverse administrative action by the PSC.</text>
    <text>All City personnel are directed to report cases of noncompliance with this policy by written MEMO (28-1418-5007) to the Facilities Security Administrator.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="committee-function">
    <heading>COMMITTEE FUNCTION</heading>
    <text>The PSC, formally known as the City-Owned/Operated Facilities Protection Pre-qualification Standards Committee, has been appointed by the Mayor and consists of the Police Commissioner and the City Purchasing Agent.</text>
    <text>The routine work of the PSC will be directed through the "City-Owned/Operated Facilities Administrator," also referred to as the Administrator in this policy.</text>
    <text>The PSC is responsible for:</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Determining the type of security personnel to be assigned to agency facilities.</li>
        <li>Type of security protection needed.</li>
        <li>Agency's ability to fund the type of security personnel-requested.</li>
        <li>Public perception.</li>
        <li>Need for trained law enforcement professional.</li>
        <li>Requirements for special security equipment.</li>
        <li>Reviewing and approving or disapproving all agency requests for security services.</li>
        <li>Pre-qualification of contractors capable of providing security services as specified by</li>
        <li>Renewal of contracts every two (2) years to include qualification or disqualification of contractors capable of providing security services specified by contract.</li>
        <li>Approval of time extensions for security services or terminating security services for cause prior to the designated stop date.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
  </para>
  <para name="agency-responsibilities">
    <heading>AGENCY RESPONSIBILITIES</heading>
    <text>Agencies are responsible for:</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Determining the need for security services.</li>
        <li>Obtaining approval from the PSC to obtain security services.</li>
        <li>Evaluating the effectiveness of services.</li>
        <li>Reporting all complaints to the Administrator.</li>
        <li>Notifying the Administrator by MEMO (28-1418-5007) of need to terminate security services for cause prior to the requested stop date or need to extend security services beyond the requested stop date. Thirty (30) calendar days' notice is required for either of the alternatives.</li>
        <li>Obtaining approval/disapproval of expenditures of funds from the Bureau of the Budget and Management Research.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
  </para>
  <para name="administrator-responsibilities">
    <heading>ADMINISTRATOR RESPONSIBILITIES</heading>
    <text>The Baltimore City Police Department's officer who has been designated as Administrator will administer the City-Owned/Operated Facilities Protection Program.</text>
    <text>The Administrator is responsible for:</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Coordinating security requests for the Committee actions.</li>
        <li>Coordinating a security requirement report on the Agency security request.</li>
        <li>Daily operation, administration, and follow-up activities of the protection	program, including any complaints relative to this policy.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
    <text>Questions relating to the protection program should be directed to the Administrator, c/o Overtime and Special Events Unit, Baltimore City Police Headquarters, 601 E. Fayette Street.</text>
  </para>
  <para name="related-procedures">
    <heading>RELATED PROCEDURES</heading>
    <text>Requesting Agency shall provide a copy of the APPROVED Request for Security Services to Department of Finance, Office of Risk Management, Division of Occupational Safety, 401 E. Fayette Street, 7th Floor, Baltimore, MD 21202 or FAX to 410-396-7278.</text>
  </para>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" effective="2004-03-11" display="true">March 11, 2004</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" effective="2016-10-19" display="true">October 19, 2016</annotation>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM-117-1-1" type="Related Policies"/>
    <annotation doc="City of Baltimore Administrative Manual" path="§AM-301-1" type="Related Policies"/>
  </annotations>
</section>
