<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Policy</prefix>
  <num>AM-002-1-2</num>
  <heading>Administrative Manual Revision Process</heading>
  <para name="scope">
    <heading>SCOPE</heading>
    <text>This policy outlines Bureau of the Budget and Management Research's (BBMR) process for requesting changes to the Administrative Manual (AM).</text>
  </para>
  <para name="pre-request-requirements">
    <heading>PRE-REQUEST REQUIREMENTS</heading>
    <para>
      <num>1.</num>
      <text>The requesting agency must draft the proposed changes and/or additions to the AM.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>2.</num>
      <text>Before submitting the proposed changes to BBMR, the requesting agency must provide a copy of the proposed changes to each affected agency (or a representative sample of affected agencies) for review and comment. Any suggestions and/or concerns received from the agencies should be carefully considered and, where appropriate, addressed in the final submission to BBMR.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>3.</num>
      <text>Any proposed additions and/or changes to the AM that impact (or have the potential to impact) the terms and/or conditions of employment for City employees must be reviewed and approved by the Department of Human Resources (DHR), the Office of the Labor Commissioner, and the Law Department. Possible union concerns should be brought to the attention of the Labor Commission for consideration and, where appropriate, resolved before the proposed policy is submitted to BBMR.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>4.</num>
      <text>In addition, any changes to the AM that involve the use of leave and/or payment processing must also be reviewed and approved by the Office of the Labor Commissioner and the Department of Finance.</text>
    </para>
  </para>
  <para name="request-format">
    <heading>REQUEST FORMAT</heading>
    <para>
      <num>1.</num>
      <text>Requests to change or update the AM should be accompanied by a memorandum, signed by the Agency Head. The memorandum should briefly summarize the proposed changes and recommend an effective date following approval of the Board of Estimates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>2.</num>
      <text>The memorandum should identify all agencies that reviewed the proposed changes.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>3.</num>
      <text>Union endorsement of a specific proposal should be noted in the memorandum. Likewise, union opposition to a particular proposal (actual or anticipated) should be noted.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>4.</num>
      <text>The memorandum should be submitted to the Budget Director and the Administrative Manual Section of BBMR at:</text>
      <text>Bureau of the Budget and Management Research</text>
      <text>469 City Hall<br/>100 N. Holliday St.<br/>Attn:	Administrative Manual Section<br/>Budget Director</text>
    </para>
  </para>
  <para name="post-request-procedure">
    <heading>POST-REQUEST PROCEDURE</heading>
    <para>
      <num>1.</num>
      <text>BBMR will coordinate interdepartmental communications to ensure all agency comments are considered and, where appropriate, incorporated into the policy.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>2.</num>
      <text>Upon the approval of the Finance Director, BBMR will prepare the letter to the Board of Estimates requesting that the proposed changes be made.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>3.</num>
      <text>The proposal will be placed on the Board's agenda.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>4.</num>
      <text>Changes will become effective within the timeframe indicated in the requesting agency's memorandum following Board approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>5.</num>
      <text>BBMR will issue a broadcast notifying all City employees of the AM changes and will place the broadcast and updated policy on BBMR's Intranet.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>6.</num>
      <text>Refer to <cite path="§AM-002-1-1">AM-002-1-1</cite> for the broadcast template.</text>
    </para>
  </para>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" effective="2012-08-22" display="true">August 22, 2012</annotation>
  </annotations>
</section>
